<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The happiness of a quiet mind both in youth and old age, with the way to attain it in a discourse occasioned by the death of Mrs. Martha Hasselborn who died March 13th, 1695/6, in the 95th year of her age / By Timothy Rogers ...</title>
            <author>Rogers, Timothy, 1658-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57578</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1851</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11977</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13574931</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13574931</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100426</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57578)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100426)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 799:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The happiness of a quiet mind both in youth and old age, with the way to attain it in a discourse occasioned by the death of Mrs. Martha Hasselborn who died March 13th, 1695/6, in the 95th year of her age / By Timothy Rogers ...</title>
                  <author>Rogers, Timothy, 1658-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 106 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Salusbury ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 106.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. 106.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hasselborn, Martha, 1600 or 1601-1696.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XL, 1 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100426:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100426:1"/>
            <p>THE HAPPINESS OF A <hi>Quiet Mind</hi> BOTH In <hi>Youth</hi> and <hi>Old Age,</hi> With the way to Attain It.</p>
            <p>In a DISCOURSE occaſioned by the Death of Mrs. <hi>Martha Haſſelborn,</hi> who died <hi>March</hi> 13th, 1695/6. in the 95th year of her Age.</p>
            <p>By <hi>TIMOTHY ROGERS,</hi> M.A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Salusbury</hi> at the <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Sun</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> MDCXCVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100426:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100426:2"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle Dedicatory. TO <hi>Mr.</hi> Jacob Haſſelborn, <hi>Merchant.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THere is nothing Men are more apt to value themſelves upon, than the being deſcended from Great and Honourable Perſons; who have either had Noble Blood running in their Veins, or have ſignalized themſelves by a ſeries of Heroical Actions for the good of their Countrey; and by this means have delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their names down to Poſterity, Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with thoſe Garlands, which the thirſt of Glory made them to deſire: And yet many thus deſcended, ſtain the Memory of their Predeceſſors; and as far as in them lies, make all their Laurels wither, by Lives led according to their own humour and fancy, and the contagious Examples of a depraved Age.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100426:3"/>
            <p>But you have the Honour to be akin to one who was on earth related to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of Heaven. Your Good Mother after having with continued Patience, ſuſtained the troubles of her weary Pilgrimage calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at length arrived at her deareſt home, where ſhe longed to be.</p>
            <p>The Remembrance of her, I doubt not, is a great help to you in your Chriſtian Race, ſuch an example of goodneſs, ſo unaffected and ſincere, whilſt it is always brightly ſhining before your Eyes, gives you both light and ſtrength to follow her, in the ſame happy path wherein ſhe went: The frequent thinking on the Holineſs of her Life, will be a great Motive to quicken you to be like her in every commendable and praiſe worthy thing. To think of her Faith, and Meekneſs and Patience, will make you flouriſh in the ſame Vertues: As young Painters encreaſe their skill, by frequently Copying old and excellent Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals. In your pious Mother you have ſeen living and exemplified Religion, a quiet Mind, not as repreſented in the coldneſs of Precepts, but as warmed and animated
<pb facs="tcp:100426:3"/>by the bleſſed Spirit, and Patient holding out to the Concluſion of a great Age; ſuch a Patience as is to be admired, but not to be deſcribed; for no Colours can be ſoft enough to draw this Admirable Grace.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> rejoyced in his beloved <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> and expreſſed a very lively plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure upon the thought of one that had very good Parents, and was himſelf ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very good: <hi>When</hi> (ſays he) <hi>I call to remembrance the unfeigned Faith that is in thee, which dwelt firſt in thy Grandmother</hi> Lois <hi>and thy Mother</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice; and I am perſwaded in thee alſo, <hi>wherefore I put thee in remembrance,</hi> &amp;c. I hope that the pure and conſtant Faith that was in your Mother is paſſed into you; not by a propagation of Blood, but of Spirit; not of Nature, but of Grace. That you and your Relations may meet her and all the bleſſed Saints with comfort at the Great Day; live to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in that place where there will be no Sin nor Pain, nor Old Age, but an Eternal Holineſs, Spring and Youth;
<pb facs="tcp:100426:4"/>and where our preſent Weakneſs ſhall be ſwallowed up of Strength, is the hearty Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Real Friend And Servant T. Rogers.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100426:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. XL. Verſe 1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I waited patiently for the Lord, and he inclined unto me, and heard my cry.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AS of all the Ages of the Life of Man, Infancy is the moſt Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and Childhood the moſt Vain, and Youth the moſt Brisk and Daring; ſo Old Age is the moſt clog'd with Pains and Miſeries. In other Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of our Journey we are annoyed now and then with Trouble and Calamity, with Sickneſs and decayes of Strength; but this laſt part of our Pilgrimage, this feeble part of Life, is its ſelf a Diſeaſe. 'Tis ſo weak, that generally the Powers of the Soul, as well as the Members of the Body, have not the Livelineſs and Vigor that they had in their greener Years; the Evening is much more
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100426:5"/>Cloudy and Tempeſtuous, more Dark and Frightful then the Morning of their Days. And yet there are found ſome Bleſſed Souls that flouriſh even in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; neither the ſharpneſs of the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor the uncomfortableneſs of the Seaſon hinders their being <hi>over Green.</hi> Such an one was <hi>David,</hi> as he was all his Life Muſically given, of an Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Heavenly Temper: in his pleaſant Angelick Airs he had often mounted up to Heaven; and at laſt, with praiſe, he took his Flight thither, to change his Hymns into ſweeter Hallelujahs. 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 29.10. <hi>He bleſſed the Lord before all the Congregation:</hi> v. 20. <hi>He ſaid to all the Congregation, Now bleſs the Lord. V.</hi> 28. He dyed in a good old Age, full of Days, Riches and Honour. So old <hi>Jacob,</hi> when the decays of Strength, and the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Age would not allow him to be long in his Devotions; he improved the more eaſie Intervals of his Illneſs to breath after God. Gen 49.18. <hi>I have waited for thy Salvation, O Lord:</hi> His Expreſſion was ſhort, but his Faith and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100426:5"/>Patience were very great. So <hi>Moſes</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared his Soul for the Joyes of Heaven, by tuning his Harp below, he Sung be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he dyed. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. And before his death he bleſſed the Children of <hi>Iſrael. Ch.</hi> 33. And after this he went up to the Mount, and put off his Body to be Cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed upon with Life and Immortality, <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.5. And good old <hi>Simeon,</hi> who had a Promiſe, that he ſhould not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part till he had ſeen the Lords Chriſt: He did not hide himſelf from the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſight, tho' he knew, that after that he muſt quickly dye; but he came by the Spirit into the Temple, and there he met with the Child Jeſus, that for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny paſt years he had long'd to ſee: And having ſeen the Bleſſed Babe, he took him up in his Arms, and was full of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſports, ſaying, <hi>Lord, now letteſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace, for mine eyes have ſeen thy Salvation,</hi> Luke 2.27, 28. I might alledge the Example of <hi>Paul the Aged,</hi> who was then in Chains, and near his Execution by the Lyon <hi>Nero;</hi> and yet after having ſerved ſeveral Years un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100426:6"/>the Banners of Chriſt, neither the Cruelties of his Impriſonment, nor the proſpect of death, nor all the weight of Age that laid upon him, did abate his hope in God; nay, his hope was ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to aſſurance, when he ſays, <hi>I have fought the good fight:</hi> He ſpoke as if he had been in Paradiſe; as if the Crown of Glory had been already on his Head; to all theſe I may joyn, <hi>that daughter of Abraham,</hi> for whom I Preach this <hi>Funeral Sermon,</hi> who ſerved God with chearful hope many years, and bore all the advances of Death, as well as her declining Age, with admirable Calmneſs and Reſignation, and long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Faith and Hope, and dyed near an Hundred Years old; dropping into the Grave like Fruit from the Tree, when 'tis fully Ripe. She had no Clouds and Darkneſs in her Soul; ſhe was all calm and ſerene; ſhe lived in Joy, and ſhe dyed in Light; ſhe ſet in Beams: And that which greatly contributed to the pleaſure of her Life, and the calmneſs of her death, was the <hi>quietneſs and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100426:6"/>ſtilneſs of her Soul;</hi> uſing frequently, upon all occaſions, this very paſſage of the Holy Prophet, <hi>I waited patiently for the Lord:</hi> From theſe words I obſerve,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That is not below the greateſt and moſt honourable Perſons to wait on God.</hi> The Grandeur of a King is no barr to his dutiful Attendance on his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker; and the Crowns of thoſe Princes ſhine with the higheſt Luſtre, that are laid at the Feet of God. Thoſe that honour him he will Honour. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels that are the Courtiers and Nobility of Heaven, and in conſtant waiting know their diſtance; and tho' they are of the higheſt rank of Creatures, they remember they are Creatures ſtill; and whilſt they wonder at the Glory of the Divine Majeſty, they know they cannot comprehend it! They do not ſit upon the Throne, but are in poſtures, full of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, employed round about it. They are very humble even in their higheſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies and cover their Faces when they cry to one another, <hi>Holy, holy, holy, is the Lord of Hoſts, the whole earth is full of his Glory,</hi> Iſa. 6.3.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:100426:7"/>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>When any affliction or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is upon us, it is our moſt becoming and moſt Advantagious Duty, to wait upon God with patience, and to pray for his relief and help.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>What is implied in this patient waiting?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. <hi>What obligations we are under to it?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. <hi>The Application.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>In this patient waiting there is included a moſt entire and free ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Will of God, as to the nature and duration of our Trouble.</hi> That it come and tarry juſt as long as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; a waiting Chriſtian looks upon his Fathers Hand, and is not with ſuch a view frighted at the moſt bitter Cup: He is not hurried away with violent Paſſions, with murmuring or uneaſie Thoughts. The Divine Wiſdom that knows when and how to deliver, produces the moſt refreſhing acquieſcence; he is not ſuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and precipitant, no fluctuation of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100426:7"/>diſcovers it ſelf in his Speech or Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.18. When the Storms are high, he is ſtill: In all varieties of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, in all the changes of his Health or Life, he is peaceable within; no Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs, no Thorns, no Canker in his Soul; he leaves the time of his Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance to his all-wiſe Creator, and waits in quiet till the time come, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out complaining or finding fault with the preſſure of the Croſs, or the ſlow advances of his help. He knows, that uneaſineſs and diſpleaſure at the Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Moſt High, is the mark of a fallen Angel, and not the Character of a Saint.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>This patient waiting upon God, is attended with Faith and Hope.</hi> With Faith concerning the reality of good to come, and with Hope concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſeaſonable fulfilling of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes that he relies upon: <hi>What wait I for, my hope is in thee, Pſ.</hi> 39. Hope is the lively Spring of Action, infuſes Life and Spirit into the feeble and the moſt humbled, but deſpair cramps and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100426:8"/>freezes, and enervates all the Powers of the Soul: It reflects upon the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Mercy of God, and makes us ſink into the loweſt depths with its kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling weight: It ſwells our Sorrows, and turns our Sighs into Roarings, and our Tears into Seas of Grief. Whereas he that patiently waits, knows that after the blackeſt Night and moſt Tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, the Sun will riſe again, and chear him with his reviving help; he knows that Celeſtial Comforts are many times Neighbours to the moſt doleful fears; and ſometimes the howling Wilderneſs is the way to <hi>Canaan,</hi> and the Waters may be troubled, when the healing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment comes; the face of the Pooll was not ſo ſmooth when the Charitable An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel deſcended as it was before, but it was more uſeful and medicinal. Never was any Seaſon more gloomy, then when our Saviour was upon the Croſs; never was any bordered with more glorious Events. It was a dark Night when he Suffered, but 'twas a glorious day when he Roſe again. He that patiently waits
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100426:8"/>remembers that the Church has been moſt dear to God, and moſt fruitful in good Works, when toſt with Storms; it has flouriſhed moſt, when the Devil and his Angels have endeavoured to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it; he waits for help, as they that watch for the Morning, they look and hope for the dawning of the Day, watch the firſt ſtreaks of riſing light, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyces to ſee it, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 130.6.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>This patient waiting upon God, is attended with earneſt deſires and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for his merciful Appearance.</hi> I wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and I cryed unto the Lord, O for that ſweet and pleaſant Hour, when I ſhall be Saved! that the time to favour me, even the ſet time were come! O that I had the Wings of a Dove, that I might flee away from the windy Storm and Tempeſt! O Lord behold my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Caſe, oh ſend me ſome help for thy mercies ſake; remember my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and thy own Promiſe; hear my groans, and perform the word on which thou haſt cauſed me to hope; do not caſt out my Prayer, do not ſuffer me
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100426:9"/>to Periſh in my low Eſtate: All this earneſtneſs is ſubmiſſive, full of Reſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Tranquility: The Sick deſire ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times to dye from wearineſs and pain; but a good Chriſtian ſhews that he is ready to depart, but is willing to ſtay till God bid him go; he waits for Chriſt with a longing craving Eye, as for a dear friend from a far Countrey; he bears his abſence with Patience, but would be very glad to ſee him come: Heaven is welcome to ſuch a panting Soul, as the Port, to one that has been frighted and endangered by the Storms; ſuch an one when confined by trouble, longs for a Releaſe, but will not break his Priſon; He waits, till the hand that Bound him ſhall break his Bands aſunder; remembring that God is as Jealous of his word, when he promiſes favours to his Children, as when he threatens pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to his obſtinate and hardned Enemies. The deſires of Perſons in diſtreſs are moſt ſerious and importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate: When <hi>Peter</hi> was like to ſink, how heartily and with all his force may we
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100426:9"/>imagine that he cryed out, <hi>Maſter ſave me, Matth.</hi> 14.30. So our <hi>Saviour,</hi> in the days of his Fleſh; uſed ſtrong Cries; and the Prayers of the Mariners in <hi>Jonas</hi> were as loud as the Storms; theſe were not more bluſtering then thoſe were affectionate. People that are juſt like to be Drowned, have no time to Compliment, their danger ſwallows up all other thoughts, but thoſe that relate to their preſent Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>This patient waiting directs the quiet Soul in ſuch a manner to God, that he uſes no undue reflections upon the Inſtruments, or more immediate occaſions of trouble.</hi> When he is ſick he does not rail at the Phyſician, becauſe he does not give him eaſe; but conſiders, that the Wiſdom of the moſt Wiſe, and the Skill of the moſt Skilful will not avail: When he is Plundered, he does not inveigh againſt the vile Engines of his Miſery, but bewails his Sin that provokes God to turn the Lyons and the Bears looſe upon him; when the <hi>Sabeans</hi> and <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans</hi> had ſpoiled the Patient <hi>Job,</hi> he calmly ſaid, <hi>The Lord hath given, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100426:10"/>the Lord hath taken,</hi> ch. 1.21. A quiet Chriſtian, when he is falſly accuſed of things that his Soul abhors; and ſees in ſuch an accuſation the hand of the Devil, uſing weak and malicious People as his Agents to Coyn and Spread his Lyes: He pities their cruel Malice; and in a Contempt of theſe mean Arts of Hell, ſays, <hi>The Lord that has choſen Jeruſalem rebuke thee:</hi> Or when he hears a <hi>Shimei</hi> rail, for ſome take delight in railing, they are a Generation of Vipers, Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Stings are in their Make and Conſtitution; to ſuch he only ſays, <hi>It may be the Lord has bid them Curſe us, Pſ.</hi> 37.7. When others are planting Thorns and Bryars to vex him, he will not torture and diſtreſs himſelf; when they wound him, hee'll not enrage and multiply the Wounds; ſuch a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an in every State is calm and quiet: He knows, that God is the Author of all Good, and the Ruler of Evil; that all his Diſeaſes have their Commiſſion from him, as the God of Nature; and all inward Troubles are under his dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100426:10"/>who is the Father of Spirits, and that in both he will be gracious and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Patient waiting upon God im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, that a man do not uſe any unlawful methods, to rid himſelf of trouble.</hi> If we uſe any ſinful arts, to eſcape from this or that Affliction, it is an argument of exhauſted Patience, and that our ſtrength is gone; 'Tis heinous unbelief, with reference both to the Power and Goodneſs of God, as if he were not able, or not inclined to help us: If we have not the preſence of our Saviour, as formerly, we muſt not with <hi>Saul</hi> go to the Witch of <hi>Eaden,</hi> or imagine that the Devil can help us when God has left us; we may in all trouble uſe all the good means for eſcape that we can; providing they be ſuch as are not inconſiſtent with the Wiſdom of a Man, or the Innocence of a Chriſtian, we are to <hi>wait on the Lord, and to keep his way.</hi> As the Eyes of an Hand-maid are fixed on her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, being ready, with patient atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to know and do her pleaſure; ſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100426:11"/>muſt our Eyes with the like dutiful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard be fixed on Heaven. The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the Goſpel are in all theſe caſes quite oppoſite to the Maxims of the <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ical Philoſophy,</hi> that gave its wiſe Men leave to end their own Lives, when they found their Pains and Griefs many and inſupportable; this indeed, as ſome obſerve, ſhewed the falſeneſs of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and this was oppoſite to other Opinions of the ſame; for they ſaid, there was no Grief, how violent ſoever, that could overwhelm a wiſe Man. <hi>Zeno</hi> the famous Author of their Sect ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led himſelf: A patient attender on God, muſt not do any thing to ſhorten or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy his own Life, by Surfeits, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Intemperance, or any other wicked Action whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>This patient waiting on God includes a conſtant perſeverance in all good Duties, till Relief and Mercy come.</hi> We muſt wait during the ſweetneſs of the Spring, and the Rigors of the Winter, when we are at eaſe, and when we are in pain; when we proſper in our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100426:11"/>and when we meet with unlook'd for ſad Events; we muſt begin to wait in Youth, and not fall till old Age ſhall Snow upon us, <hi>Job</hi> 14.14. as a Sentinel keeps his Poſt till he be Relieved, if help come not this hour or moment, it may the next: We ſhall never be aſhamed of our hope, if afflictions do nee'r ſo cloſely Beſiege us, our Saviour in due time will march to our aſſiſtance, and reward our Courage and Fidelity, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13. The Husbandman waits for the precious Fruit of the Earth, notwithſtanding he now and then ſees unſeaſonable weather, and very ſharp Seaſons, yet nothing does abate his hope of Harveſt; he knows the joyful day will ſurely come; he does not tarry lazily at home, when the Seaſon does invite him to Sow his Seed; he rouzes himſelf, ſummons his Servants, and all in earneſt go to work together; he is not diſcouraged with a ſtormy day, nor folds his Hands becauſe the Sun does not ſhine, nor the wind blow as he would have it, <hi>Ecceſ.</hi> 11.14. But alas, how many excuſes do we make, to evade
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100426:12"/>our Duty and put it off; 'tis too hot or too cold, too ſoon or too late to begin to work; many will not be good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the days are bad, they'll not travel, becauſe they are afraid of Rain; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as that Rain they fear might lay the duſt, that affliction they meet with in the Road, might deliver them from thoſe hurrying cares that at other times blind their Eyes, and obſoure their Judgments. Let us take heed leaſt the Patience of the Husbandman condemn our peeviſhneſs, and our fearful haſte, who if we have not help immediately think, we are undone; whereas, that quiet Son of <hi>Adam,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Ploughed his Ground and Sown his Seed, takes no further care about it, but leaves the reſt to the Influence of Heaven, and the God of Nature: He quietly waits for the Harveſt; and for the Rain that plumps the Corn; he would not cut it down when it firſt begins to ſpring above the Ground, but ſtays till 'tis fully ripe. Thoſe Chriſtians that are in darkneſs ſhould conſider, that <hi>Light is ſown for the Righteous, Pſ.</hi> 92.11.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100426:12"/>Let us not deſire to reap before the time, not with a vain labour ſtrive to haſten the Months of Harveſt, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.24. We ſhall reap in good time, our Salvation is nearer then when we firſt believed, and we may with the Husbandman find a deal of work to do before the Harveſt come. So a Chriſtian knows, if no Salvation from trouble come in this World, yet Death will ſet him free; and then the tedious hours of pain, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn no more for ever: 'Tis very hard indeed long to wait it, very grievous to Fleſh and Blood; but its highly agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the brightneſs of our Faith, and the greatneſs of our Hopes; for what is this poor ſhort Life to a long Eternity? <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the reſt of the waiting Saints, are now at reſt in the full enjoyment of their bleſſed Hopes: Long Attendance upon God, ſhews a firmneſs of uncommon Courage, and a moſt profound Humility. Whereas, to be angry and uneaſie, that we are not delivered juſt when and how we pleaſe, betrays too great an Opinion of our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100426:13"/>ſelves; for if we were leſs proud, we ſhould be more patient; if we thought of what we deſerve, we ſhould not mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure at the burden that is laid upon us, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.11. The haſtineſs of <hi>Saul</hi> brought on his Ruine; he could not wait, and ſo he Rebelled; he acted as if he had been bewitched, for the Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Princes againſt God, as well as of their Subjects againſt them, is as the ſin of Witchcraft; but to ſtay till he that ſends trouble think fit to call it off, ſhews a temper truely Chriſtian, and is an evidence of a ſubdued and a reſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> We are to conſider the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> that ſhould oblige us to this patient Waiting.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 1. <hi>We ſhould patiently wait on God for our many miſeries and ſorrows, call for ſuch a frame of Soul.</hi> The Thorns in our fleſh, and the troubles of our minds, our pains and our fears call for it; our Voyage to Heaven may prove very full of Storms, and by this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100426:13"/>patience we ſhall eſcape Shipwrack, and not be left to the mercy of the Waves, but have a wiſe Pilot to ſteer us, and a ſure Anchor within the veil: God may give the Devil leave to vex us, an Angel of Satan may buffet us, he may torture and diſtreſs us very ſore, tho' he have not leave to kill us. The roaring of the Lyon makes the Beaſt tremble, tho' they are not within his devouring Jaws. The Devil is often inſtrumental to bring ſickneſs and pain upon us: The worſt of Men ſerve for common Executioners, and the baſeſt of Spirits may ſerve to bring Judgments. And beſides, God will have no Creature uſeleſs; even Storms and Vapours, and Lightning and Thunder fulfil his Will: But now by our patient hope in God, the Malice of the Devil will be turned to Good; his buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feting will teach us the need we have of Chriſt, it will make us watchful, it will make us full of gentleneſs and pity, to ſuch as he falls upon, when we are eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped our Bowels will earn over them: This waiting upon God will reconcile
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100426:14"/>us to the moſt painful, and the ſharpeſt methods of his Providence; this diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points the Devil, who would have us when the hand of God ſmites us, to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment our own Souls; he will be diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed if we are not fretful tho' we be diſeaſed; by patient waiting we pull out the ſting of troubles; we Conquer Sin, that would otherwiſe embitter all our Comforts, and rob us of our Peace and Hope, and make God to be our Enemy, and every frown of his is more frightful and aſtoniſhing then the united threats of Men: Every touch of his hand is heavier then their combined ſtrength; one drop of his Anger will overwhelm us more then the floods of many Waters: Innumerable Evils in this Life will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault us, both as we are Men and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and therefore we have need of Patience; Patience to ſteer a right courſe to Heaven; for we ſhall meet with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rough and contrary Winds, that will blow upon us from every quarter: On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by this quietneſs of waiting we ſhall be happy, as to have no Tempeſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100426:14"/>though there may be Storms abroad. We have need of Patience, for we may meet with many Tribulations that will ſhake our confidence, and put our ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Faith to a very ſharp Tryal, and make the bruiſed Reed bend very much, though it do not break. If we have never ſo many years of ſmiling ſhining Light, the days of darkneſs will at length come, and the ſhadowes of the Evening be ſtretched out: Our greener Youth knows but little ſorrow, but it hangs with a mighty weight upon decaying age. A thouſand Miſeries come crouding thick upon old folks; and after all theſe, comes the ſhady veil and bitter death. When we ſtand upon the ſhoar, and view the bluſtering Winds and the rough Seas that we are to encounter, ſurely we need a deal of patience of waiting, and of prayer; and our great afflictions will not be well born, with a little Grace: fiery Tryals will conſume us if we are not fortifyed before we are thrown into the Furnace. We need a vaſt Treaſore of Grace, when we conſider, what paint
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100426:15"/>we may live to feel, and what ſtinging troubles and provocations we may meet withal.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 2. <hi>We ſhould patiently wait upon God, for by our moſt painful troubles he deſigns our Welfare;</hi> and if we are not wanting to our ſelves in a due improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Croſſes, we may reap un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable advantages: The ruggedneſs of Adverſity may be more uſeful to us, than all the ſmoothneſs of our moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clouded and moſt eaſie days, our Souls may thrive with the faireſt and moſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting qualities: When our Bodies languiſh and decay, as 'tis commonly obſerved, that the People in cold Northern Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, are more robuſt and longer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, than thoſe that are nearer to the South, who are daily broiled with exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive heats, which, by quick degrees, melt their Lives away. In our moſt overflowing afflictions, we are like thoſe that are at Sea; <hi>Pſ.</hi> 107.24. <hi>We ſee the works of the Lord, and his wonders in the deep,</hi> a thouſand ſtrange things are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to them that are in the midſt of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100426:15"/>the gaping Waves; that are not ſeen by thoſe that are upon the Land; they ſee the wonders of his Power in their ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, the wonders of his Wiſdom, in finding out ways to ſave them in the midſt of danger. We ſhould particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly wait on God in all our ſickneſs, for he then teaches us to know our ſelves, our weakneſs, our ignorance, and the folly of our careleſs unthinking health; he teaches us to ſee, that we and others in our beſt eſtate are altogether Vanity. The ſmartneſs of our pains makes thoſe inſtructions that are given us by the Rod, to be more remembred and more abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, we cannot after bitter experience forget what a terrible thing Sin is, that makes our Body pine, and our Souls droop. Our troubles that are deep and laſting, teach us to ſee, that none of our fellow Creatures in the very height of their Grandeur and Proſperity are to be the marks of our envy: for they may in one moment be as low as we. We that have been ſcorcht with fiery Tryals, muſt pity thoſe poor Men that have been
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100426:16"/>ſinged in the Flames: We ſhould not be uneaſie nor grieved at the Croſs, for our pain will ſoon be paſt, and our paſt pain gives a mighty reliſh to our preſent eaſe; and we may hope that in the midſt of thoſe Sorrows that God ſends, he will give us the moſt refreſhing diſcoveries of his Love, and by the Inconveniencies that ſieze our Bodies, remedy and aboliſh the far greater diſorders of our Souls; ſuch as unbelief and ignorance, and ſelf-conceit, and vain glory, and a too great admiration of the world. No Books, nor no Preachers can teach us that which our own painful feeling and ſenſation does; a few days ſickneſs cauſes a mighty alteration in all our thoughts, and apprehenſions; by this we judge of all things, by a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and a truer Light. We look upon this alluring world with other fort of eyes then we did before; all its paint and varniſh does not change its bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quality, nor after having ſeen it at the borders of the Grave, can we think it beautiful or doat upon it: And ſuch a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100426:16"/>diſcovery we then make of our ſelves and our own evil hearts, as we never had before. We could not have imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that our Faith had been ſo weak, till the Storms came and made us tremble. While we are in a calm, and on the quiet ſhore, we do not ſo well know our weakneſs; but when we put out to Sea, and have loſt the ſight of Land, and the Wind and Waves roar about us, then we are amazed and aſtoniſhed. All the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinal ſtroaks of God to his Servants, are the product of his Love: He could take all their Burdens off in one moment, but he ſees that their Faith and Patience in the midſt of troubles, is beneficial to themſelves and others: Without ſome of the calmneſs that is in their Souls, this World would be an Hell, a Region of blaſphemous diſcontent in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions; his People have a dearer love to Chriſt, and new manifeſtations of his faithfulneſs, and of the wiſdom of his Conduct.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 3. <hi>This quiet waiting upon God makes us in all ſickneſs, pain and trouble,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100426:17"/>eaſie to our ſelves and others.</hi> It makes us poſſeſs our Souls in patience; but to be fretful and peeviſh, and quarrelſome at our burden, makes it more burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and ſplits one croſs into a thouſand; fills our bitter Cup, and makes that which before was but half full, to run over with Gall and Wormwood; a fore uneaſie temper of mind, makes us that we cannot reſt in any poſture, and no Pillar will be ſoft enough for us, when we Crown our Heads with Thorns, an uneaſie diſquietneſs of Spirit approaches near to the tormenting fury of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Hell is an abode of horrible rage and diſcontent; they are ever angry at God, and at themſelves, continually burnt with Flaming thoughts: But a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Soul is like the milky way, no Clouds obſcure the brightneſs of his Grace: He ſhines with a croud of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces joined together: His Innocent ſenſe of grief, and his expreſſions of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, fall like the drops of dew in the ſilent Night; they fall very gently: and where-ever they come, they make
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100426:17"/>all very green and flouriſhing. The words of the patient edify the by ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and ſhew to them the ſtrength and beauty of Religion. What an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractiveneſs is there in a compoſed quiet Soul. How Serene! how Lovely! 'tis entertained with Muſick, lives and dyes in Harmony. When Storms are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, all is ſtill within; but an impatient man vexes himſelf and others, runs upon the Rocks and ſuffers Shipwrack; he is overloaded with anxious cares, and ſinks beneath the bulky weight, and often in his proſperity he is overſet with too much ſail, his pride and ambition, with too ſtrong a gale, blow him on the ſhelves. Let us therefore ſtrive to keep our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits under Government, for the Scorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of a Feaver, and all the violence with which it preys upon the blood, are not ſurer indications of abated Health, then tumultuous fluctuating paſſions, and diſcontented thoughts, and murmuring expreſſions are of a bad ſtate of Soul.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 4. <hi>Becauſe ſuch evil days may come upon us, wherein we ſhall by our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100426:18"/>age and trouble be unqualified for active ſervice.</hi> We need patiently wait, for it may be long before our Sorrows have a period. Many a weary ſtep may we have to take, and many a burden to bear, before we come to our Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys end. The time may come, when nothing that offers it ſelf to your Eye, your Ear, or your Taſt, will give you pleaſure; and you'll neither be fit for buſineſs nor recreation; and the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of your graces will ſhare in the decays of your age. When you are a burden to your ſelf, you'll find no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in other things. Not all the gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur of preferment could tempt old <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zillai</hi> to a Court Life; and you'll be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little capable of Spiritual Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, when your faculties are weak. When old age with its pale attendants ſhall ſieze upon us, it will be very well, if in the Winter of our Life there be any vigour in our hope: All the Oyl we have put into our Lamps, will be little enough to ſerve us in our paſſage through the dark and ſhady veil. We
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100426:18"/>are to take great care, leaſt when the Night comes, our Stock and Treaſure of Grace ſhould be ſpent; and we ſhall find it hard to have inward livelineſs and health, when our outward Man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cays. 'Twill be hard to rouze our Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to new Conflicts, when we come lagging like weary Soldiers from the field of Battle. We can go but a very flow pace towards Heaven, when old age has maimed us, and when our Blood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to freez and ſtagnate in our Veins. In this nearneſs to the Grave, People are generally ſo very feeble, that they are fit for nothing. They are bleſſed, that in circumſtances ſo afflicted, have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed calmneſs and reſignation, and can pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently wait. For by this means a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Harveſt, and ſweet and eaſie thoughts will ariſe in thoſe furrows that are Ploughed with Age; and while their Foreheads are wrinkled, the face of their Soul will be very ſmooth: No thorny cares, no weeds nor thiſtles will be grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there. In ſuch a caſe, if you pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently wait, you will have the root of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100426:19"/>the matter; and that Root will be fixed like ſome ſtately Cedar, that has taken deep hold and is not eaſily torn up; keeps its Station when its leaves are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len off. In the withering decays of Age, you cannot indeed run very faſt in the ways of God, but you may travel by ſoft and eaſie Journeys to the Grave, and your Souls be recreated with the bright views of Heaven, whilſt your Bodies ſtoop with the weight of many years. Tho' your hearing fail, you'll be ſaluted by good News from within; Muſick will be in your own breaſt, when the Daughters thereof are brought low. And you'll have this happineſs in the want of that ſenſe, that you'll hear no ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders nor ſad tidings. When your guſt and reliſh of other things is gone, you'll feed upon the Bread of Life: When your Eyes are ſunk your heart will be in Heaven: And when your Memory is failed, God will not forget you; His word will be the ſtaff that your totte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Age may lean upon.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:100426:19"/>
            <p>Reaſ. 5. <hi>By patient waiting upon God we ſhall have renewed ſtrength, and freſh Experience of his Love;</hi> We ſhall have help both for our Bodies and our Souls; a Life of patience tends to its own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; keeps the humours from over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing their juſt bounds, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits from irregular fermentation; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the peeviſh and impatient chafe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a continued Fever, and their ſtrength declines and evaporates. It's ſaid, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.3. That <hi>the man Moſes was very meek, above all the men that were upon the face of the earth:</hi> And in Ch. 34.7. <hi>He was an hundred and twenty years old; when he dyed his eyes were not dim, nor his natural force aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> He had as a man may ſay, a ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Winter, or a youthful Age, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining unperiſht vigour in every part. 'Tis moſt certain, that patient waiting upon God, will make him not to ſend thoſe Judgments that waſte and ſhorten Life; ſuch as are thoſe raging Plagues, Famines and Devaſtations, which ſend many thouſands early to the Grave: We
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100426:20"/>ſhall by this means not paſs our days in his wrath. An aged Chriſtian that has been patient for many years, comes at length, like a Veſſel richly laden home, after a tedious and ſtormy Voyage, full of reviving Experiences of the Divine Goodneſs, from the Morning to the Noon, and to the Evening of his Life. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 71.17, 18. He calls to mind with joy the various and admirable conduct of his Heavenly Father, and ſleeps in quiet on the lap of Providence. Seeing with what beautiful Wiſdom he had laid the ſoundation of his Happineſs, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Structure; how he healed his Diſeaſes, and has ſafely brought him to the borders of a perfect cure: How they were planted as Trees of Righteouſneſs, and by various Acts of Love and Power maintained in the Vineyard; how they were in pain, and how they were eaſed with his tender hand; how they wept in agonies, and how he wiped their tears away; new ſupport ariſes to the patient holy Soul, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.31. It haſtens our eſcape from trouble; as the ſtilneſs and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100426:20"/>compoſure of any Perſon in a Fever, tends to mitigate its force; but a reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs agitation of the Body, does more and more inflame and fire the Blood. By ſuffering we learn to ſuffer, and patience reconciles us to the Croſs, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 27.14. No ſtudied arguments, no fine Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces do ſo fortify the Soul in trouble as its own experience: This is the Leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of anxious and unquiet thoughts; gives a ſecret refreſhing, and a mighty ſtrength; this pours balm into thoſe Wounds, that otherwiſe might gangreen and feſter; when clog'd with outward infirmities, and when there are the marks and ſigns of a falling habitation; there will be the proſpect of an houſe not made with hands; and when death is in the windows, there will be ſtrength in the heart.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 6. <hi>This patient waiting does moſt excellently prepare for the mercies waited for,</hi> and gives them when they come the ſweeteſt reliſh; they are welcome as reſt to weary Travellers, that long to be at home. When God and a waiting
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100426:21"/>Soul meet together, What tranſports and joys are there? <hi>O he is come, he is come, that I long'd to ſee!</hi> it revives me to hear his chearing Language, to ſee his ſmiling face. In what an extaſie was Old <hi>Simeon,</hi> whilſt he embraced his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; many a long year had he waited for the bleſſed ſight. O happy eyes that ſaw that Sun begin his Race! hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Arms that embraced and hugg'd ſo great a Treaſure! <hi>Luke</hi> 2.36. O what a joy to a Father, to ſee a Prodigal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning home, after he had long ſtayed and waited for his return? With what Muſick, with what Joys, with what Feaſts does he ſolemnize ſuch a pleaſant day? Thus 'tis reported of <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s mother, what a concern ſhe had for her Son, he was the daily Subject of her Prayers and Tears; that St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten when ſhe mourned, ſent her away with this Anſwer, <hi>That it was not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that a Child of ſo many Prayers ſhould periſh.</hi> No ſooner was he Converted, but her Spirit was at eaſe, and ſhe now deſired no more. He tells us in his <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:100426:21"/>that when the day approacht that his Mother was to paſs to a better Life, as they were talking together of the joys of Heaven; in the Concluſion of this Conference, which was the moſt agreeable in all the World; ſhe ſaid to me, <hi>My Son, I avow to you, that as to what relates to my ſelf, that I have now no further hopes nor pleaſure in this world: I know not what I do here, for I have nothing more to look for. The only thing that made me deſirous to live, was to ſee thee a good Chriſtian before my death; now my good God has granted me ſo great a favour, as to ſee thee become entirely his Servant, by the contempt that thou hast of all the goods and pleaſures of this Life, Why then do I tarry here any longer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reaſ. 7. <hi>It cures the frowardneſs of our ſpirits in our laſt ſickneſs, and makes death very happy,</hi> and Heaven very ſweet, not an unbecoming thought nor word of God. The Concluſion of ſuch a ſerene Life, is ſtill and fair as the Evening of a Summers day: Such an one is not puſht
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100426:22"/>or hurryed out of the World; but walks out as from one Room into another; ſleeps in death, with the compoſure of an Infant ſucking at its Mothers Breaſt; they go by a ſmooth deſcent to death: ſome without much pain; tho' but rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is that exemption from the aſſaults of the laſt Enemy granted. Some are laid down very gently on their bed of duſt, and others with groans and ſighs extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the dwindgling lamp of Life. A pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Soul is ready, and if God give the word, it gladly flies away; it longs and flutters to be gone; and in the part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moment, ſuch an one ſhall not be left: a Convoy of Angels ſhall wait upon it, to ſee it ſafe through all the Regions of the Air, where the Evil Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits would diſpute its paſſage to Glory. Oh how welcome is Heaven to a troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led weary Soul! How welcome are Hallelujah's to one, that upon Earth heard the ſlanders and reproaches of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a bitter Tongue; the Clouds of Life are then ſcattered, and there ſucceeds an eternal day: Then patience has no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100426:22"/>work, for there is no pain; there hope is vaniſh't, for the Good that was once deſired is poſſeſt. The calm of that quiet Region into which we enter after death, will make amends for all the Storms we met with in the way thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. How many Bleſſed Souls ſhall we meet that were in Storms as well as we? that were ſick and tempted, and ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and afflicted, that had weak Bodies and fearful Spirits? and to go thither from ſuch a World as this, from the Subburbs of Hell into the New <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> Tho' we are in Tempeſts, yet we are not to live upon the Sea. Our Life may be very calamitous, but 'tis alſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhort: Tho' loaded with bitter and uneaſie griefs, yet in Heaven there is no more ſorrow, for there is no ſin: there will be light in our Minds, peace in our Conſciences, and comfort in our Hearts; there will be no more fear in the place of Eternal Love, no trembling doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Soul in all the vaſt Aſſembly: they cannot queſtion whether they Love Chriſt or not, when they are with him.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100426:23"/>All their former ſuſpicions are turned into pleaſant wonder, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.2. Its an Honour to be in Chriſt betimes, an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be Chriſt's Diſciple, and much more Honourable to be in his glorious Temple. Oh Bleſſed are they that are at their Journeys end, after having wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed long for God; he ſeeing they could find no durable reſt below, put out his hand, and took them into his Ark above. How can we almoſt forbear congratula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe happy Souls, that <hi>have fought the good fight of faith,</hi> and have got the Victory. While we ſin they are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely pure; they Rejoyce while we Mourn: tho' thanks be to God we mourn in hope; what we pray for, they enjoy. When we ſee theſe calm and patient Chriſtians going to Heaven; we ſay, <hi>O our fathers, our fathers, the Horſmen of Iſrael, and the Chariots thereof,</hi> ye were our Defence and our Glory; we can hardly forbear ſaying, Oh that we were with you, why have you left us behind? but you were in Chriſt before us, and are with him ſooner; you entered into
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100426:23"/>the Vineyard ſooner, and ſo before us are rewarded; we will indeavour to tread in your ſteps; then you and we, nay Jeſus, our deareſt Jeſus and we ſhall meet together! I often think of that place, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.1, 2. becauſe ſo many af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and miſeries, and judgments, are the portion of the Living. Bleſſed are they that ſleep in the quiet Grave, no more terrified with Dreams, no more complain of reſtleſs Nights, and of Months of Vanity; no more do they hear the Confuſions and Diſorders of our World. And to the quietneſs of our ſlumbers there, nothing contributes more than patient waiting when we are alive. How did <hi>Jacob</hi> bleſs his Sons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he dyed? and how ſweetly did he yield his Breath? <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.3. O happy death to wait for God's Salvation, and to ſee the Salvation that he waited for; Salvation carries a very pleaſant ſound; but the Salvation of a God is very great and glorious. The hope of this ſweetens the lives of the bleſſed Heirs of Heaven; it pulls out the thorns of ſickneſs, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100426:24"/>the ſting of death; it relieves their age; it makes the Grave to loſe its horrour; it makes their Bed of duſt very ſoft; they live in motion, and they reſt in peace: They exhauſt their Spirits in the work of God; but they never come to the dregs of Life, for theirs is clear and pure to the very bottom.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Exhortations to thoſe that have patiently watied on God even in Old Age.</head>
               <p>Reflect. 1. <hi>How gracious he has been to you, in giving you many years, wherein to get Oyl, and to trim your Lamps,</hi> and to prepare for another World. How many ſtorms have you out-lived that made others ſink? Many, many young People are gone to Judgment a great while ago, while that Hand that cruſht them, has been very gentle and merciful to you. You have ſurvived the dangers, and the ſins, and the giddineſs of Youth, and are now almoſt at our Journeys end.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Endeavour to do good to others, that have not had ſuch experience of God
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100426:24"/>as you.</hi> Thus you bring forth fruit in old age, and are fat and flouriſhing, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 92.14. you do, as it were, grow young again, with a vaſt acceſſion to your Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſtature. When you are full of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and by your Example and your Words declare to others how faithful and how kind God has been to you: So, by teaching them knowledge, you will rekindle and inflame your own Light; whilſt others younger then you decay, you ſhall thrive and proſper. He that planted you makes the green Tree to wither, and the dry to grow. You'll not only go to Heaven fully ripe for Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, like a ſhock of Corn gathered in due ſeaſon, but there will be ſomething for others to glean when you are gone: And in the mean time Summer and Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Youth and Old Age, doe as it were meet in you; the decays of one, and the fruitfulneſs of the other. In your Evening there is Light, <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.4, 5. Fortifie your ſelves with the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences of God, goodneſs whenever your patience is like to tire, as <hi>Polycarp</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:100426:25"/>ſaid, when he was urged by the Procon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul to deny Chriſt, or to do ſomething like it: <hi>Theſe fourſcore and ſix Tears, have I ſerved Christ, and he never did me any harm; and how can I then bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheme my Maſter and my Saviour.</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort others to fear, and love, and truſt God, as you have done; by your Holy Awe and Reverence, ſeek upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions to Correct their Lightneſs and their Vanity. You have ſerved a good Maſter, and you have had the Honour to ſerve him very long; be not now wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his work, be not now for going out of his Vineyard, when he that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed you, is juſt coming to reward your diligence. Be of good Courage, <hi>The Lord is at hand; O ye aged People bleſs the Lord</hi> your Preſerver, and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſing his praiſe; let your Winter, as well as the Spring of Youth, praiſe the Lord. How few have had that time for Heaven, that you have had? Oh the bleſſed Seaſons and Days of Grace, that you have had! It's a wonderful Honour to thoſe that are old, that they have ſo
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100426:25"/>large a ſpace, wherein to do a World of Good, to enlarge the Kingdom of Chriſt, and to make their future Crown more weighty: And none ſhould grudge to labour for fourſcore or an hundred Years, when for ſo ſhort a Duration of painful Diligence, he ſhall have an Everlaſting Recompence. By living to old Age, you have more Wiſdom, and Experience, and Skill, than others; your Graver Years teach you to beware of ſeveral Rocks that they ſplit upon. And all theſe Mercies are heightned to ſuch as arrive to an Healthful old Age, not loaded with the uſual Pains and Griefs, and Languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Motions of decaying Age, for then the longer the Life, the more the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 14.10, 11. Thus Life does ſmoothly take its courſe, without meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with great Obſtructions in the way, and is not only Long but Happy too. This was the peculiar Felicity of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs before the Flood, their Lives were extended to almoſt a thouſand Years, and yet we read of none of thoſe Sad Symptoms attending them, that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100426:26"/>us now at fourſcore, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.10. It's a very comfortable thing, to have neither a poor nor ſickly Age, neither to want Neceſſaries, nor to be in Pain: 'Tis a Bleſſing to live to ſee your Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and a greater Joy to ſee them walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Truth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 128.6. but yet none can expect to be freed from the evil days mentioned <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.1. full of trembling Palſies, grievous Aches, lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering Pains, and innumerable Evils; but if you patiently wait on God, and improve well your declining Years, you'll at length be ſatisfied with living as 'tis ſaid of <hi>Job,</hi> Chap. 42.17. <hi>He died, being old and full of days.</hi> He roſe as from a Feaſt, not Surfeited, but well pleaſed with the Joys and Plenty of his latter Days. He was once indeed in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Frame, when his Spirits were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clouded with Melancholy, and his Soul was burnt with Anguiſh, when he had reſtleſs Pain by day, and no ſweet Sleep at night, <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.4. then he wiſh'd for any ſort of Death, tho' Shameful and Untimely, tho' Violent and Uncommon,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100426:26"/>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 5, 16. But this was more <hi>Job</hi>'s Diſeaſe than his Grace, 'twas a moſt raſh and haſty Wiſh; to die in Terror and Anguiſh, is a forlorn and doleful way of dying: He eagerly thirſted for the Grave, but at laſt he looked upon it with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eye, and went to it as a weary Traveller goes to Bed: He looked for the finiſhing of his Courſe with ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive regular Deſires, and Quiet Hopes: So refreſh'd and ſatisfied with living, are thoſe that are good in Age, but a <hi>Sinner an hundred year old is accurſed.</hi> Curſed in his neglect of the Buſineſs of Life, Curſed as condemned by a perpetual De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Longer and Longer Time, he is pained with Trouble, and afraid to die. The Sins of his Youth have a Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in his Thoughts, and ſcare him with the ſight of Death, as knowing they will not only lye down with him in the Grave, but riſe with him thence. And yet amidſt ſuch hideous Views and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, he has an unquenchable and painful Thirſt after thoſe Pleaſures that are paſt away: His Luſt is freſh and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100426:27"/>lively when his Head is grey; every thing about him grows old but his Sin; and a long Life to ſuch an one, is but a continued Load of Guilt, a daily trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring up of Wrath againſt the Great Day: But nothing is more Decent or more Lovely, than to ſee a remaining Green under the Snow of Age: The Beauty of an old Man, is his Grace as well as his Years: To be full of Days, and to be full of Grace, full of Faith, and Hope, and Joy in God, is to be as beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful as ever any was in the moſt bloom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gayeſt Youth. <hi>Job</hi> 5.26. <hi>Thou ſhalt come to thy Grave in a full Age, like as a Shock of Corn cometh in his ſeaſon.</hi> It ſheds and ſpoils if it ſtay too long, if it be not gathered when 'tis fully Ripe, and the Seaſon of it is as well loſt, as when 'tis taken too green. Do you that are Old, take care of all the Evils proper to your advanced Age, of Peeviſhneſs, and Moroſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Sourneſs, and Covetouſneſs; and let thoſe that are Young, be Temperate and Sober, and uſeful to the World, that they may either live to be old, or get to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100426:27"/>Heaven betimes. Do you that are Aged improve your leiſure Hours to prepare for your Change; and do you that are Young, liſten to the Speeches and Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of thoſe that are near their latter end. In your old Age recreate your ſelves with looking forward to a better State; and when you do but very faintly draw your Breath, yet be breathing after Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and your ſincere Sighs and Groans ſhall be as acceptable as all the Motions of your ſwifter Youth: And when your Tongues begin to faulter, let your Actions ſpeak your Patience and Submiſſion to the Will of God: And when you are even like to ſink with Pains and Miſeries, Oh remember you are almoſt at home; you have but a little while to run, and you ſhall obtain; a little while to fight, and you ſhall be Crowned: Watch a little longer, the Sun is juſt ſetting, and in a few Moments you may be allowed to go to ſleep; there is but a little Sand left in your Glaſs; your Life is like a Candle burnt quite to the bottom: And though the Religion of young People is very
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:100426:28"/>pleaſant in the Eye of God, their Graces ſend forth a ſweet Perfume; and when he walks in his Garden, 'tis agreeable to him to ſee the moiſt Flowers breath out their Morning Incenſe; yet he loves old Diſciples too, and he gives them his Word and his Promiſe for their tottering Age to rely upon. Be ſure to improve the lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of your declining Years to the beſt Purpoſes, and be thankful that you are now retiring from the Noiſe and Hurry of the diſagreeing buſie World. As Sir <hi>Henry Wotton</hi> ſaid after a kind of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous Life, I have a great Advantage from my God, that makes the Out-goings of the Morning to Praiſe him; I daily magnifie him for his particular Mercy, of an Exemption from Buſineſs, a quiet Mind, and a liberal Maintenance, even in this part of my Life, when my Age and Infirmities ſeem to ſound a Retreat from the Pleaſures of this World, and invite me to Contemplation, in which I have ever taken the greateſt Felicity. You may make uſe of all the Remembrances of the places where you have lived, to help you
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:100426:28"/>in the beſt things. As Mr. <hi>Walton</hi> tells us of the aforeſaid Politician, that he ſaid upon his being in his old Age in <hi>Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> School, My being in this School, and ſeeing the very place where I ſate when I was a Boy, occaſioned me to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Thoughts of my Youth that then poſſeſſed me, Sweet Thoughts indeed, that promiſed my growing Years nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Pleaſures, without mixtures of Cares; and thoſe to be enjoyed, when time (which therefore I thought ſlow paced) had changed my Youth into Manhood: But Age and Experience have taught me, thoſe were but empty Hopes; for I have always found it true, as my Saviour did foretel, <hi>Sufficient to the day is the Evil thereof.</hi> I have, ſays he to Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> then of <hi>Eaton,</hi> in my paſſage to my Grave, met with moſt of thoſe Joys of which a diſcurſive Soul is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and have not wanted thoſe that were inferior. Nevertheleſs, I have not in this Voyage always floated on a Calm Sea, but have often met with croſs Winds and Storms, with many Troubles of Mind,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:100426:29"/>and Temptations to Evil. And yet though I have been and am a Man compaſs'd about with Humane Frailties, Almighty God has, by his Grace, kept me from making Shipwrack of Faith and a good Conſcience, the thought of which is now the Joy of my Heart, and I moſt humbly praiſe him for it; and I humbly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that it was not my ſelf, but he, that hath kept me to this great Age, and let him take the Glory of his Mercy. And now my dear Friend, continues he, I now ſee that I draw near my Harbour of Death; that Harbour that will ſecure me from all the future Storms and Waves of this reſtleſs World; and I praiſe God I am willing to leave it, and expect a better; that World, wherein dwelleth Righteouſneſs. And to him I add the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Mr. <hi>George Herbert,</hi> that bleſſed Man, that <hi>other David,</hi> that tuned his Soul with Heavenly Thoughts, and Muſically lived, and Muſically died. Mr. <hi>Walton</hi> in his Life tells us, that in the time of his laſt Decays, he did often thus expreſs himſelf to Mr. <hi>Woodnot</hi> and his other
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:100426:29"/>Friends, that attended him in his Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Condition.</p>
               <p>I now look back upon the Pleaſures of my Life paſt, and ſee the Content I have taken in Beauty, in Wit, in Muſick, and pleaſant Converſation are now all paſt by me, like a Dream, or as a Shadow that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns not, and are all now become dead to me, or I to them: And I ſee, that as my Father and Generation has done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, ſo I alſo ſhall now ſuddenly (with <hi>Job</hi>) <hi>make my Bed in the dark</hi> and I praiſe God I am prepared for it; and I praiſe him that I am not to learn Patience, now I ſtand in ſuch need of it, and that I have practiſed Mortification, and endeavoured to die daily, that I might not die Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally: And my Hope is, that I ſhall ſhortly leave this Valley of Tears, and be free from all Fevers and Pain: And which will be a more Happy Condition, I ſhall be free from Sin, and all the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations and Anxieties that attend it; and this being paſt, I ſhall dwell in the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> dwell there with Men made perfect; dwell where theſe Eyes ſhall
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:100426:30"/>ſee my Maſter and Saviour Jeſus, and with him ſee my Relations and my Friends: But I muſt die, or not come to that happy Place; and this is my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that I am going daily towards it; and that every day that I have lived, hath taken a part of my appointed time from me: And that I ſhall live the leſs time for having lived thus, and the day paſt — And to another he ſaid, My dear Friend, I am ſorry that I have nothing to preſent to my merciful God but Sin and Miſery; but the firſt is pardoned, and a few hours will now put a period to the latter.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Do not murmur, if ſome that began to wait upon God later than you, yet have more Joys.</hi> He is gracious to you ſtill, and he may do with his own what he will. Though it is your Privilege to have ſerved him long, yet remember you are at the beſt, and when you have done all, but unprofitable Servants; they that came in later to the Vineyard, may have as much Joy as you, but you have as much as you deſerve: He may give
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:100426:30"/>to his Returning Prodigals very noble Entertainment, but you that are elder are not excluded from the Feaſt, you may come and taſte of the Fatted Calf, and ſhare in all the Feſtival Solemnities and Joys of others. The Surlineſs of the elder Brother in the Parable, diſcovered a great deal of Spiritual Pride; made him undutiful to his Father, and unkind to his Brother, whom in Union to his Father's Carriage, he ſhould have welcom'd home. There was in all the Behaviour towards him, nothing of Injuſtice or Partiality, he took nothing from the Elder to give the Younger, he did not ſtrip him to cloath his Brother. Can you who are Aged murmur who muſt have Heaven at laſt? In the mean time God is yours, all that he hath is yours, his Son, his Word and Promiſes, and Innumerable Bleſſings. It ſhould rejoyce you, to think that theſe younger Servants of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter may prove eminent Inſtruments of his Glory, when you are at reſt from your Labours.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:100426:31"/>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>With humble reliance on the Grace of God, endeavour to perſevere in his Service to the laſt moments of your Lives.</hi> You have done a great deal for Chriſt, which is matter of Joy, but you have done it all with his aſſiſtance, which is matter of Humility, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.9, 10. Alas, how little have you done for God, of what you might have done: It was a great Favour to you, that you did not grow old among his Enemies; but it is a Favour that obliges you to a particular Acknowledgment. Oh take heed leaſt <hi>having begun in the Spirit, you end in the Fleſh,</hi> and degenerate to Formality and Worldlineſs, and a vain Religion: Take heed leaſt your <hi>latter end be not worſe than your beginning;</hi> Paul <hi>the Aged, and a Priſoner, was ſtill doing good,</hi> Philem. 9. Some will ſay I have laboured ſo hard, and done ſo much, I hope I may now ſit ſtill and take mine eaſe. You muſt labour till your laſt Sand be run; you muſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour from your firſt Morning to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of your day, from your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to your Death; and you muſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:100426:31"/>ſtrive that your laſt days may be your beſt.</p>
               <p>To all ſuch aged Servants of our Lord, ſo Steddy, ſo Religious, and ſo Fruitful, there is a great Reverence due from young People: We muſt not deſpiſe thoſe that are Old, for if we live we ſhall be ſo too, and then others may with juſtice treat us as we treated them; a good old Man or Woman are never to be ſpoke of, but with terms of Reſpect, and not with ſuch a ſlight Air, and jearing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous ſort of Expreſſion, that is uſual with many giddy People; with all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable deference does St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak of <hi>Andronicus</hi> and <hi>Junia who were in Christ before him,</hi> Rom. 16.7. And as <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerves, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.31. <hi>The heary head is a Crown of Glory, if it be found in the way of Righteouſneſs,</hi> that is, Old Age is very honourable, if it do not diſhonour it ſelf by a Courſe of wicked Actions. The wiſe King intimates, that a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect is to be paid to one who has long travelled in the beſt way, ſomewhat re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling that which is to be given to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:100426:32"/>a Crowned Head. It's a moſt comely thing to ſee Grace ripening with the Maturity of Age; and the number of Services to God and Men, bearing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion with the number of increaſing Years: Old Age, though decrepit, is honourable, like the Ruins of ſome noble Palace, there remains in the Fragments of the ſtately Structure, ſome Graceful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Beauty, ſomething uncommon and Magnificent. It may be ſaid of Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a long ſtanding, as of <hi>old Gold, old painting, Sculpture, Statuary and Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecture;</hi> the Pieces that have moſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, are generally moſt valuable, their Duration does not leſſen, but increaſe their Excellence: Good old Age is, to the true diſcerners of things, full of Wonder and Obſervation, as in a Winter or a Froſt Landskip may be expreſſed a curious deal of Art, though ſuch as are young Practitioners in Painting, may perhaps be more affected with thoſe Deſcriptions that repreſent the blooming Spring. 'Tis certain that Perſons advanced in years and Grace, have a more eſtabliſh'd Love
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:100426:32"/>to God than younger People; and we may, as to this, prefer their more grounded Knowledge, before that of ſuch as have been but a while tutored and diſciplin'd in the School of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The more General <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> IN all your Troubles, to further your patient waiting upon God, be ſure to pray unto him for Support, or for Deliverance. When St. <hi>Paul</hi> had a Thorn in the Fleſh, a painful Diſeaſe, that created as much trouble to him, as a Thorn uſually does in the tender Fleſh; <hi>He ſought the Lord thrice,</hi> which denotes his earneſtneſs and his fervent Deſire to have the Croſs removed; as to that he was not heard, but he obtained ſufficient Grace, which was infinitely better than external Eaſe and Comfort: Say when you are deeply diſtreſſed, <hi>O Maſter ſave me or elſe I periſh:</hi> And when Troubles increaſe, we muſt renew our Cries, as the Mariners double their Cable of the Anchor
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:100426:33"/>when the Storm grows more furious; and it is far from being a Sin, to pray againſt violent and ſharp Afflictions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it argues a right Knowledge of our own Weakneſs, and that we are not able to bear a Burden that is very heavy? We may lawfully deſire to be freed from te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, and lingering, and ſharp Pain, for the length of it is a very great Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. There are two things which we may pray againſt, 1. <hi>Reproach,</hi> That like ſome Indian Poiſons Murthers us by ſlow degrees, and ſhoots its envenomed Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows in the dark, we are wounded, and we know not who it is that bends the Bow; the blaſting of our good name, is <hi>a Perſecution of the worſt kind,</hi> 'tis one of the moſt refined Stratagems of Hell; and ſuch as <hi>ſlander</hi> their Neighbour, either know not what they do, and then they are Fools, or they do it wilfully, and then they are Devils, they ſmell rank of Fire and Brimſtone: Some are as forward to put off all the Productions of their gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>green'd ulcerated Spirits, as if they had got a Patent for Lying, as if they had
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:100426:33"/>engroſs'd and monopoliz'd this Sin; they think a little Backbiting has no great harm in it, whereas there may be Death in a Whiſper, as well as Murther in a Wiſh. We may pray againſt <hi>Anguiſh</hi> and <hi>Terror</hi> of Soul, which is like a fiery Furnace and ſcorches us on every ſide, and imbitters all that others call the Pleaſures and the Sweets of Life: Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially muſt we pray, that when ſickneſs or pain robs us of our Health, ſin may not at the ſame time rob us of our Faith and Hope in God: as alſo that it would pleaſe him not to allow Satan to rake in our wounds; and when his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty hand has ſmitten us, that he would not leave his Enemy and ours to touch us to the Quick as he did <hi>Job:</hi> and that at laſt all his malice may be defeated, and that thirſt extinguiſhed whereby he ſo eagerly thirſts and longs for our Ruine; and if we patiently wait, we muſt in all our Pains maintain a moſt entire Compliance with the Will of our Corrector, both as to the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance and removal of our Sufferings:
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:100426:34"/>And while they laſt, let us open with all the freedom imaginable our whole Caſe, and all its circumſtances to the Father of our Spirits; and when we open our Griefs, his Bowels will earn over us: our very miſeries have with him a pleading and a moving Eloquence. <hi>This poor man cryed, and the Lord heard him.</hi> You may cry to the Lord, which implies a vehement eager motion of the Soul, and an outward expreſſion of your ſenſe of Grief: The beſt of men have not been inſenſible of pain and trouble; <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> and the other Patriarchs felt theſe Inconveniences of Life as well as other men. 'Tis ſaid of <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 48.1. that he was ſick; and <hi>ver.</hi> 10. that <hi>his eyes were dim for age, ſo that he could not ſee:</hi> he was bedrid ſometime before his death, and no doubt had his Groans and his Crys like other Aged men. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> with all his Muſick could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve an undecaying Youth, nor charm away the cold Winter of his Life. When <hi>he was old and ſtricken in years, they co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:100426:34"/>him with clothes, but he got no heat,</hi> 1 Kings 1.1. And in other ſeaſons of his Life, he ſays, the preſſure of his grief was ſo very weighty, that it made him <hi>groan all the night,</hi> and he was <hi>weary with his groaning, and his bed ſwimmed</hi> in an inundation of overflow-Tears, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 6.6. and Pſ. 38.8. <hi>I am fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſore broken: I have roared by reaſon of the diſquietneſs of my heart.</hi> This Roaring, notes the Loudneſs and Vehemence of his Cries. And ſays the poor deſolate <hi>Job,</hi> when his <hi>melancholy</hi> and terrors were upon him, chap. 30.28. <hi>I went mourning without the Sun: I ſtood to and cryed in the Congregation.</hi> I had, during my tempeſtuous Night, ſcarce a glimpſe or beam of Joy. I was in ſuch flaming Anguiſh, that ſcorcht my Body, and preyed upon my Soul; I was in ſuch dreadful and amazing fears that I, was not able to keep ſilence. My inward torment, even when I was in any publick Aſſembly, made me ſhriek and cry aloud. And <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſays of his ſick and languiſhing condition, Iſa. 38.14.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:100426:35"/>
                  <hi>Like a Crane or a Swallow, ſo did I chatter; I did mourn as a Dove.</hi> His Cry was quick, and frequent, and loud, and frightful; with a very ſorrowful and doleful Tone: His Eyes failed with waiting, and his Heart was even like to break. Theſe Examples I alledge to ſhew you that the beſt of men may be ſenſible of pain, and yet be ſubmiſſive to the Author of it. Loud Groans and Crys are no marks of an inward Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and diſorder; for by theſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Nature gives it ſelf a little vent, and it gives a little eaſe, tho' indeed but very little; becauſe our returning Grief makes our Groans and Crys return. Tho' they are innocent and unavoidable expreſſions of ſome weighty ſorrow that is like to cruſh us. Grace does not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow Nature, tho' it corrects all its exceſſes and diſorders. We know that the Language of the Sick has not the livelyneſs the briskneſs and ſtrength of thoſe that ſpeak in health: their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, their Looks, their Actions, their words are all changed. All indeed are
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:100426:35"/>not equally ſenſible, for ſome perſons have a finer ſet and contexture of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and conſequently a quicker ſenſe of Pain than thoſe that are of a heavier and duller Conſtitution. The delicate tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Body of our Saviour, was more ſuſceptible of grief than the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the Thieves that were Crucified with him.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. <hi>When you pray, do not wonder if you are not immediately anſwered:</hi> do not murmure at the ſlow pace of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Mercy. You ſhall have help in the moſt beautiful ſeaſon, when the glory of God and your good may be moſt promoted. If he as yet delay to hear your very earneſt and importunate Crys, remember that <hi>his Elect cry to him day and night,</hi> and he will at length avenge their Cauſe. The <hi>Souls under the Altar cry;</hi> all Nature, Groans and Crys to be eaſed of the miſeries that our ſin has brought upon it. We muſt pray, but not preſame to tell our Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor what, and when he is to give. 'Tis an excellent poſture to be found
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:100426:36"/>waiting on our Knees, tho' mercy and deliverance come not juſt when we would have it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Thoſe things which we many times moſt earneſtly ask might be vaſtly prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to us.</hi> Many an one ſays, give me this or that or elſe I die; and the very things they prayed for, when obtained, prove a curſe; and thoſe in which they hoped to rejoyce many years, ſend them betimes mourning to the grave. <hi>Rachel</hi> ſaid to <hi>Jacob,</hi> give me Children, or elſe I die. There was in her ſpeech a great deal of childiſh weakneſs and impatience: She hoped the having a Child, would prolong her life, and ſhe ſmarted for her wiſh, ſhe died in her Lying In. Many are very importunate with God, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will ſerve them but this or that particular Comfort, I muſt have it, or I am undone; and when they have the Idolized Vanity that they doted on, they quickly find cauſe to repent of their haſty follies. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were fond of a <hi>King,</hi> but they had a long time wherein to repent of that fondneſs.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:100426:36"/>You may perhaps have what you ask, but you may have it with a frown, with ſuch diſpleaſure as will change your Wine to Vinegar; and your ſmootheſt delights into the rougheſt thorns, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.31. It is a friendly act of God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe us often what we ask, when it is really for our hurt; and to ſave us from our miſguided wiſhes is the love and kindneſs of a Father. If <hi>Paul</hi> had had his thorn removed immediately he might too greatly ſwell with his Gifts and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations, or be like a <hi>Saul</hi> again.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. <hi>Tho' God do not immediately hear our Crys, yet he may gratifie us in better things. Moſes</hi> begged to enter into <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> but he had no remaining longing after that happy Land, when he was once in Heaven. The joys of Paradiſe had with him a ſweeter taſte than all the Milk and Honey of that could ever give. We have no cauſe to grumble that our Suits too long depend, if in the delays of deſired help, he now and then gives us a ſight of his amiable Face: The Croſs will not overwhelm us, when his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:100426:37"/>Arms are underneath: when, tho' he do not remove the Cup, yet he ſweetens it with his Love: he delays to ſave us to try our faith, and to make his Salvation more illuſtrious. As <hi>Jeſus,</hi> tho' he heard that <hi>Lazarus</hi> was ſick, <hi>Joh.</hi> xi. 6, 7. he did not haſten to his dying Friend, as knowing he intended to glorifie his power in his Reſurrection.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>He delays an immediate Anſwer to our Crys, to ſee whether we can patiently wait, and believe his promiſe, when we have no ſenſible proofs of his good will.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> we will continue Suppliants when he ſeems to chide us from his preſence. This is an evidence of confirmed patience when we abide waiting at his door, tho' for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral hours or days he ſeems to take no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of our Crys.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>He ſuffers us to wait a long time before he hear our Crys, to bring our ſins to remembrance;</hi> and to put us in mind how we uſed him, how long, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a tedious hour we made him ſtay before we bid him welcome to our hearts,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:100426:37"/>a long time he knockt e're we let him in: It's no wonder that he uſes us as we uſed him, 'tis a moſt equitable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable retaliation, that we ſhould taſt of the Fruit that we have planted.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>He loves to ſee his Servants in a praying poſture,</hi> for it is an argument of Love and of Humility; their Tears are botled; he knows that theſe Sorrows, like <hi>April</hi> ſhowers, will make them more fruitful afterwards; and that by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they learn to pray; and the frequent returns of duty make them to perform it with greater zeal and skill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>As to your Crys to God for help in trouble, obſerve theſe Rules.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Be ſure to offer up all your Crys in the Name of Chriſt,</hi> and all the while you pray think of his kind, and compaſſionate, and prevailing Interceſſion. Cry in his Name for you are encouraged ſo to do, from his Promiſes, from the vertue of his Blood and Merits, from his nearneſs to God, and his Love to you. You find <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.23. that he was praying on the Mountain when his Diſciples were in a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:100426:38"/>ſtorm at Sea. As he ſuffers not in all our Agitations, ſo he is not unmindful of our Troubles: when we are toſt hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and thither by the changes of our Bodys or our Souls; <hi>He is the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever,</hi> Heb. 13.8. How many Gulphs would ſwallow us up, and againſt how many Rocks ſhould we be daſht if it were not for the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful and tender remembrance of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. Let us under every Croſs pray to God in his Name; for by his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings we are reconciled, and have acceſs to the Throne of Grace, a Throne ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Blood; whereas without him we had trembled at the Bar of ſtrict Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: And he prays for us, not only as a Favourite, but as the Surety of the Covenant; not meerly by intreaties, but in the vertue of his Blood. And when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we make mention of his bleſſed Name, it muſt be with the loweſt reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, with a due apprehenſion of our unworthineſs, and an high value of the Love and Grace of Chriſt; and take care to avoid whatſoever may obſtruct
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:100426:38"/>the ſucceſs of your repeated Crys. For ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>Ye ask and receive not, becauſe ye ask amiſs,</hi> James 4.3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>When you have Prayed and Cryed, look for an anſwer of your Prayers.</hi> Let not your Requeſts be ſhot at random, propoſe to your ſelves ſome good end, and ſee whether you have obtained it. If you have asked peace of Soul, enquire whether all be ſtill within, and whether his Light has ſhined upon you with its chearing Beams. If you have beg'd Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, enquire whether you have more willingneſs to ſuffer; and ſo in all other Caſes it argues that we perform our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as a Task, and from a ſlaviſh tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or a cold indifference, when we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver concern our ſelves for the ſucceſs: and it is a with-holding of that Glory that is due to God; for upon every an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of our prayers we ſhould give him freſh Acts of Praiſe. If we have a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion depending in any Court, as we wait with hope, ſo we fail not on all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to enquire whether it be remembred and kindly received; and whether we
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:100426:39"/>are like to have what we petitioned for. But if we neglect to review this part of ſolemn Worſhip, we loſe that truſt and hope that we might have had, and we weaken our own hands. For to mind our anſwered prayers would encreaſe our Love, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.1. and our neighbours fare the worſe for this Omiſſion, we do not incourage and invite them to praiſe God with us.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Wonder greatly that ſuch poor Crys as yours ſhould reach Heaven.</hi> It was matter of great thought to <hi>Solomon,</hi> when he ſaid, 1 Kings 8.27. <hi>Will God indeed dwell on the Earth?</hi> He that has all the ſpatious Heavens for his Circuit and Dominion, will he not only viſit this Earth, but dwell there? So may you ſay, will he whoſe Court is throng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Angels and happy Saints, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard ſuch a poor Wretch as I? Will he that ſits upon a Throne regard me a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner on this Earth? Will he that is ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with Hallelujah's, regard my ſight, my groans, my tears? Oh what Grace is this! What adorable condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion!
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:100426:39"/>I know he would not regard me, but for the ſake of Chriſt; <hi>Glory be then given to him that fits upon the Throne, and to the Lamb.</hi> I am not worthy to look towards Heaven, what am I then that my prayers ſhould reach thither, and enter, and be recorded, and anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there? A poor Beggar is not diſdained by the King of Kings, he does not trample on a worm, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 34.3, 6. O what am I that I ſhould be admitted into the Preſence, and have audience of the King of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; <hi>Lord what is man, or the ſon of man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How ſhall I know that God has heard my Cry, and that my patient waiting has not been in vain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>If he beſtow upon you the very thing that you requeſted:</hi> If after your cry for eaſe you are eaſed; if you are recovered after you have prayed to be brought from the Gates of Death? If after having had many ſollicitous thoughts about your being falſly accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, God is at length pleaſed to ſcatter the Cloud, and make your Innocence appear to the ſhame of your malicious
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:100426:40"/>Enemies? Thus <hi>Jabez</hi> prayed in 1 Chro. 4.10. <hi>That God would bleſs him, and enlarge his Coaſt. And he granted him that which he requeſted.</hi> It was a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abundant kindneſs to one deſirous of Grandeur and Dominion, for <hi>Jabez</hi> might have been a very happy man, tho' his Coaſt had not been enlarged; he might have governed and enjoyed himſelf and his Friends in a little room; and he might have gone to Heaven by the way of grief.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Your Crys are heard when God gives you reſignation to his Will,</hi> even in the abſence of that which you moſt eagerly deſired: if after having poured out your ſupplications, you return from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence chearful, and eaſie, and well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, leaving him that is inſinitely wiſe to do with you and your Bodies, with you and your Friends, what ſeems beſt to him: when you find your hearts unbro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with anxious cares and ſolicitude whether you are gratified or no: This ſecret contentment is a foretaſt of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and a pledge and inſtance of Divine Love.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:100426:40"/>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>'Tis a moſt certain ſign of your Cry, being heard, when even in the delays, of the deſired Comfort, you love God more than you ever did.</hi> When your thoughts of him are more frequent and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: when your love to all his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and even to paintful Duties is increaſed, and that you are thankful for the ſmalleſt mercies, for the ſmalleſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervals of pain and trouble; and when even <hi>in the way of his judgments you wait for him;</hi> by all which you may plainly perceive that your prayers may be heard when your affliction is not removed, and many times the Mercies may be given, and they are ſo ſudden or ſurprizing, that you ſcarce can believe your ſelves delivered, even when you are delivered, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.1. and <hi>Acts</hi> 12.14. tho' they had the faith to pray for <hi>Peter,</hi> they had not the faith to believe that he was eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped, and knocking at the door.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Second General Head, in order to your patient waiting upon God, you muſt endeavour to keep up in your minds
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:100426:41"/>good and honourable thoughts of him all the while you are in trouble.</hi> It is with great induſtry and art that the Devil takes occaſion from our affliction to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs us with unbecoming thoughts of him that is our beſt Friend: and to make him, during our dark and gloomy ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to paſs for an Enemy; as the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in the ſtorm miſtook their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Saviour for a Spirit; and in hideous conſternation ſhouted out, as thinking ſome Evil Spirit was come to make their Death more terrible, for they looked upon themſelves as juſt drowning. If we have irregular appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of God, as rigorous and inexo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably ſevere, as rouzing up the greatneſs of his Power to cruſh and ruine us, ſuch undue thoughts breed black and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious fears, and ſhrink all the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our minds with deſpairing unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief; our minds are weakned and cramp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the terror of our thoughts; and the conſequent of this will be, that we ſhall either give him no ſervice, or that which is very trifling, and full of vain
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:100426:41"/>and idle Ceremonies: For to ſuch a ſort of pompous inſincere Worſhip does Superſtition lead thoſe poor People, whoſe Eyes are hoodwink't and blinded with it. Under our dark miſtaken thoughts of God and his Deſigns, our Obedience is the Action of a Slave; 'tis with unwillingneſs and conſtraint that we Obey, retaining at the ſame time a diſpoſition to throw off the Yoak. We proceed in our Devotions like thoſe that Row in Galleys; 'tis with a backward Heart, and an unwilling Shrug. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we give to our Maker, is with a convulſt and ſtingy Hand; for we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend him as a ſevere and a rugged Maſter, as full of ſtern and ghaſtly Majeſty. Now to remedy theſe uneaſie fears, our Saviour came into this World, to give us admiring thoughts of God, to repreſent him as aimable and worthy to be delighted in; to make him the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of our Truſt and Hope, and not of our Dread: As a Benefactor, or a moſt liberal Phyſician moſt tender and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate, that wounds us in order to a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:100426:42"/>laſting Cure; and his Spirit is ſent to promote our Love to him: and St. <hi>John,</hi> whoſe Soul was moſt full of Love, was the moſt beloved. God has in a great meaſure left off dealing with Men in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible terrors, as he did heretofore. Nay, ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>Tho' we know the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the Lord,</hi> yet 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. we perſwade Men, we uſe towards them the moſt gentle, and ſoft, and eaſie Methods; we are to ſay to them, <hi>Behold the Lamb of God, that takes away the ſins of the world;</hi> and there is nothing frightful in him, that has all the tender Qualities of one of the meekeſt of all Animals, a Lamb.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>If you would patiently wait upon God, beware of having only little Faith.</hi> We are not to lay the blame of our being troubled ſo much on the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our danger, as on the weakneſs of our Faith; when we doubt and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then, with <hi>Peter</hi> in the Storm, we begin to ſink. That our Faith may grow, we muſt uſe all the good means we can to enlarge our knowledge of God and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:100426:42"/>Chriſt; for the dwarfiſhneſs of our truſt, is owing to the darkneſs of our Minds; <hi>They that know thy Name will truſt in thee.</hi> Knowledge of its ſelf does not produce this admirable reliance of the Soul: The Devils are very Learned and Knowing Spirits, but their Light does only ſerve to ſcortch them; it gives no comelineſs to their horrid ſhape, nor to their Flaming Torments any Relaxation: But ſuch a Knowledge as is founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Love and Hope, and ſweet Experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Truths and Mercies of God, will convey to us great degrees of Strength. In order to remove our lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Faith, we may make frequent and delightful uſe of Chriſt; we muſt run to his Arms with all the ſpeed and force we can; and by being near to him, we ſhall learn to bear the Croſſes of this Life; and how to long for that which is to come. Such whoſe Faith is rooted and ſpread to a mighty breadth, and of a tall Stature, ſcruple none of the greateſt Tribulations; and many of them
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:100426:43"/>go to Heaven with as much calmneſs, as if they were but going into another Room, or changing their Rags for a new Suit of Cloaths. But a little Faith ſhivers and trembles, and is loath to go hence, as amazed at the painfulneſs of the Paſſage, and the greatneſs of the Change. In no caſe let us blame God for his Rigor, but our ſelves for our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief. In this Life we are expoſed to very great Tryals, and theſe will not be patiently born with a little Patience. O! What a Conteſt is there between great Storms and little Faith? The time will come, when we ſhall wiſh to have had more Oyl in our Lamps, and more Grace in ſtore againſt an evil day; when the Devil and his Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Diſeaſes, and pale and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Death, with all his mourning Train of Evils will ſet upon us; How ſhall we meet ſuch Enemies, without well-poliſht Armour on? What ſhall the Sick, and the Lame, and the Blind, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crip't do, in the day of Battle? Will not our little Faith be a moſt unkind
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:100426:43"/>and diſingenious return to the great Love of Chriſt? How unſuitably do theſe two look, his Love in its ſtrength, and our Faith in its decay; his Love in its flouriſhing perfection, and our Faith wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and lyable to be extinguiſhed, almoſt with every little breath? And our grief will be encreaſed from the time we had wherein to prepare for all the ſorrows that might come upon us; the leiſure and the helps of many Years: But if our Faith be ſtrong we ſhall not be diſcouraged with the delays of God; we ſhall <hi>truſt him tho' he kill us,</hi> and caſt our Anchor in the dark; we ſhall look to, even an abſent Saviour; and wait for his Salvation, when there is no deliverance within the Ken and View of Senſe, when all other reſuge fails; when all the Greatures cannot help us, even in the moſt threatning and the laſt extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; when we ſee no light, we ſhall caſt our ſelves at the Power and Love of God.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>If you would patiently wait upon God in trouble,</hi> you muſt have ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:100426:44"/>
                  <hi>promiſes to rely upon.</hi> You have but ſmall encouragement to wait, if you have no promiſe that your waiting ſhall not be in vain: We are not with vexatious labour to pain our ſelves, by ſtretching our thoughts too much upon futurity; or to plunge our ſelves into the unfathomable depths, to know the ſecret decrees of God. Our Eyes are too weak to read the Records of Heaven, and they are far diſtant from our Sight: But it is more eaſie and profitable to look into the <hi>Revelation,</hi> that is made to conduct our lives, both in Proſperity and in Trouble; and in this Revelation there are abundance of very reviving Promiſes for the moſt trembling Soul to rely upon. And all thoſe are moſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely true, not like thoſe of many Men in high Places, who draw along ſuch as wait upon them, with large Promiſes, moſt kind Looks, and obliging Words, but never think much of what they Promiſe; and ſo make the poor Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of Preferment, at length to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way aſhamed; after having ſpent a deal
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:100426:44"/>of time, and perhaps Money too, to no purpoſe: And ſo all they gain is a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle bought Wit, which alas they dearly bought, with the Circulation of many torturing and unquiet Hopes. But it often happens, that they go away both with their Heads and their Purſes empty. But now <hi>they that wait upon the Lord, ſhall not be aſhamed of their hope,</hi> Pſal. 34.5. Pſal. 25.3. they ſhall at length obtain what God hath promiſed, and what they waited for.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>That you may patiently wait upon God, remember how many kind expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences you have had of his love hitherto,</hi> 2 Cor. 1.10. Without this Reflection, you'll be ſtartled at your new Tryals: But no <hi>Goliah,</hi> with all his ſtalking Greatneſs and his big Words, will make you quit the Field; if you conſider how God has often ſecured you from as near and as bulky dangers; from the hiſſing Serpents that were ſwollen with Venom, and ready to ſpit it all upon you; and from <hi>the paw of the Lyon and the Bear:</hi> But unleſs we call to mind the <hi>years of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:100426:45"/>the right hand of the most High,</hi> every preſent Storm will always ſeem the moſt bluſtering, and every preſent pain the moſt ſharp, it will be a moſt unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing for us now to ſink, when we have been formerly delivered from as near and as great Calamities. That arm that ſaved us once, is not now ſhortned that it cannot ſave: The ſweet Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences we have had of God, ſhould cauſe us to be aſſured, that when we wait on him we do not wait in vain; and no Evidence can give us ſo unſhaken a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, both of his Being and his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, as thoſe inward taſts and reliſhes of his Love. This inward Senſation is extreamly quieting; 'tis a beam of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Light: Nor can we by any trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, how long or how ſharp ſoever, be forced to quit our Religion and our Faith, when we have once felt the joy and pleaſure of them. A good Man has Two Harveſts every Year, one from the Furrows of the Field, and another from his own Thoughts. Such efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Faith, diffuſes a vital warmth over
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:100426:45"/>every faculty, and is no more to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from a Chriſtian, than he can be divorced from himſelf; and keeps the pleaſed recreated Soul from being liſtleſs and indiſpoſed, from being chilled and frozen with exceſſive fear and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh. To have a Treaſury of Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences whereto to have recourſe, is the Priviledge of thoſe that are arrived to a good old Age; every year of their Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, they have had new Experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the kindneſs of their unerring Guide; they can look back and ſee won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Mercy and Deliverance. O! What a Catalogue of joyful paſſages of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers its ſelf to their Obſervation? How often they were dying, and God made them to recover; how often they were ſinking and afraid, and he bid them be of good Courage. It's comfortable to old People to have a great deal of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney by them, which they got in the Spring and Summer of their Active Life: It ſupplies their wants, makes their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants reſpectful, and the decays of weary Age more tolerable, when they
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:100426:46"/>cannot work for a livelihood as they uſed to do. But O! How much more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable is it to be <hi>Rich in Faith,</hi> ſuch their good Maſter looks upon with a pitiful and watchful Eye: He takes care of their weakneſs, as all good People have a great kindneſs for an old Servant, that has lived many years in their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Very Honourable and Bleſſed is that Age, that has been long faithful to God. Beſides, Such as have been care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to remember their Experiences of his Mercies, may plead them with hope in Prayer, <hi>Judg.</hi> 15.18. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.7. Lord, thou haſt been my Father hitherto, be not now my Enemy; thou haſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore dealt graciouſly with me, do not now overwhelm me with the weight of numerous and too great Afflictions: In other diſtreſſes I have had thy Preſence, O be not now a ſtranger to me!</p>
               <p>Sixthly, <hi>That you may patiently wait on God, maintain in your Spirits a great indifference to the things of this World;</hi> that you may be prepared upon the firſt Summons to take your flight from it:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:100426:46"/>Regard without concern or too paſſionate Affection all that is dear to you in this Life; and while you are on Earth, let your Eye be on Heaven. Ceaſe to live to ſin, that you may not be torn from your Enjoyments; but bid them farewel without a ſigh: by a continued progreſs in Mortification, you will out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grow that anxiety of thought which others have, as to what ſhall befal the World or themſelves; this Earth by moſt of its Inhabitants is over-rated, and ſo they are loath to quit it.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, <hi>That you may patiently wait on God, keep your Eye most conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſteddily fixed on your bleſſed Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi> When the Storms ariſe, look on him whoſe Power can in a moment make the Sea calm, and the lowring Skie clear again: In your trouble look to your Helper, as when we ford a deep River, we look to the further ſide. Whereas, if we only pore upon our Miſeries, we tire our Spirits, and raiſe to our ſelves more hideous proſpects of Calamity. You need not go far to ſee your Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:100426:47"/>for he is with you in your Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, in your Cloſets; he is in the Scriptures, and in all the Promiſes; no part of the World is out of his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and he has all Power in Heaven and Earth. The Prince of the Air that is limited to his own Principality, and to his changeable Empire, cannot raiſe a Storm without his leave; tho' he is in himſelf very powerful, yet he is Subject to a greater Power. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle directs the Chriſtians of his days to <hi>wait for the Lord from Heaven,</hi> 2 Theſ. 3.5. To wait for the ſight of that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Perſon on whom they have belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, with whom they hope to live for ever; the ſight of him is what they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly long for. It will be an Heaven to ſee him who has done ſo much for them, and of whom they have heard ſo very much: When he comes, he will reward his patient Servants; he will manifeſt their Grace, and make the World to wonder at his Power in their ſupport: <hi>Behold the Faith and Patience of the Saints.</hi> Thus in the Text, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:100426:47"/>ſays, <hi>I have waited for the Lord.</hi> I have not waited ſo much for mine own Exaltation or the Conqueſt of mine Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as for the Favour and the Love of God. I have not long'd to ſee mine Houſe flouriſh, and my Friends enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or my Name perpetually celebrated on Earth. No, truly Lord, I have long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for thee, and thee alone. This is all my Satisfaction, this is all my Deſire; tho' no Deliverance come, yet if thou, O my God, doſt thy ſelf come, I ſhall have enough. Another ſort of Spirit have thoſe who are only of this World, they all would climb, and are uneaſie to attain ſome high or Lofty things. Oh that I were Honourable ſays the Rich; and O that I were Rich, ſays the Poor Man: Every one that has Money would fain have more, and he that has a deal of Land, would fain be Maſter of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Field; he that is obſcure would fain be noted; and he that is publickly talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, would fain be more popular. Theſe are the things they long and wait for; not ſatisfied with what God thinks
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:100426:48"/>fit to give them. Even Princes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times think they have not room enough, unleſs they invade the Dominions of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as well as lord it in their own. And <hi>Ahab</hi> a wicked King, could find no pleaſure in his Crown, unleſs he had the Vineyard of honeſt <hi>Nabaoth.</hi> But be you ſatisfied with whatever is allotted you by Providence; and do not grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble if you meet with Pain, Reproach, Poverty, and various Croſſes: For all the Saints in Heaven, went through great Tribulations thither; moſt of the Illeſſed Saints performed their Voyage to that happy Land.</p>
               <p>And now I come to ſpeak of our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted Friend Mrs. <hi>Haſſelborn,</hi> who dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Month, in the 95th Year of her Age; in a good old Age indeed. Few, very few of all the Sons and Daughters of <hi>Adam,</hi> have, in theſe times of the World ſo long a Life: few of thoſe that dye of Age, hold out ſo long as ſhe. I ſhall make no manner of excuſes, nor tell you, whilſt I am praiſing her, that
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:100426:48"/>I am not for praiſing thoſe that are De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted; nor confute my ſelf, as ſome do, that ſay they are againſt commending the Dead, even when they ſay of them all that ever they can. Our Saviour ſaid of this or that Perſon, <hi>O Woman, great is thy Faith;</hi> and he that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends his Saints when they live, would not have their Memory roughly treated when they are Dead. No body will ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the Humble <hi>Jeſus</hi> as guilty of Flattery, or of over-admiring any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and yet what a large Character does he think fit to give of his Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, <hi>Matth.</hi> XI. 11. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, among them that are born of Women, there has not riſen a greater then John the Baptiſt.</hi> And the plain-hearted free-ſpoken <hi>Paul,</hi> that never never balked the boldeſt truth, or the moſt ſearching reproof; yet he was not ſo moroſe, as to chide the People for commending <hi>Dorcas,</hi> for her good Work, and Alms-deed, for the Coats and Garments which ſhe made, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.36. Nay, ſo far was he from ſo four a temper, that he high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:100426:49"/>extols <hi>Andronicus</hi> and <hi>Junias</hi> who were <hi>in Chriſt before him, and who were of note among the Apostles.</hi> It is a fault not to commend good People, if it be done with truth and modeſty; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in an ill-natured Age, where thoſe that God will own as his Jewels, are tramp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on; and thoſe that he will commend and accept are Cenſured and Reproacht, though for their <hi>hard ſpeeches</hi> that Men utter againſt the Innocent, they muſt be rigorouſly Judged; therefore, for my part, I reckon it my Duty to contribute what I can to embalm the Memory of ſuch as were dear to Chriſt on Earth, and now live with him above. All the Graces of the bleſſed Spirit, are too va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable to be neglected or obſcured in the dark: We are to invite others to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the aimableneſs and beauty of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; behold how it ſhines and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs, and ſpreads its healing Beams. <hi>Behold, an Iſraelite indeed,</hi> John 1.47. And it's an Encouragement to others to be good, when they find <hi>their works ſhall praiſe them in the gates of Zion,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:100426:49"/>it ſhall be ſaid, this or that man was born there;</hi> we ought with great freeneſs and candor to acknowledge the Gifts and Graces that are beſtowed on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Let us not bury the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their excellent Actions in the Grave: Thus we may lawfully give them Praiſe, while we do not give them Worſhip. We think the <hi>Virgin Mother bleſſed among Women, and to all Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhe is bleſſed:</hi> We will honour her Memory, but never think ſhe is above her Son; nor will we take the Crown from his Head, to place it upon hers: We will imitate the Examples of the Saints Departed, but not pray to them; for <hi>even Abraham himſelf is ignorant of us.</hi> In preſerving the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of good People, we act ſuitably to the Deſign of God, who has taken care to Record ſeveral of his Excellent Servants, of whom we otherwiſe had never heard: As they were zealous for his Glory whilſt they were alive, he will not let their Names be trampled on with
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:100426:50"/>the Feet of Pride, when they are De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted: Such Perſons are like withered Flowers: In their flouriſhing Condition they recreated and pleaſed their Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the ſweet Odours of their Charity, their Meekneſs and their good Works. For when the Flower and the Green is Blaſted by the cold of Death, they are after all, like the tender Plants Medicinal, even when dryed and in their moſt unbeautiful State, of great uſe and ſervice to the World. The Scripture per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuates the Memory of ſeveral good Women, as well as Men, as <hi>Sarah,</hi> and <hi>Rebeccah,</hi> and <hi>Rachel,</hi> and <hi>Miraim,</hi> and <hi>Hannah,</hi> and <hi>Deborah,</hi> and the Bleſſed Virgin; and that affectionate Perſon, that ſcrupled no coſt to ſhew her reſpect to our Saviour, Mark 14.9. <hi>And Jeſus loved Martha, and her Siſter, and Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> John 11.5. He often met with a welcome at their Hoſpitable Houſe. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> greets <hi>Priſcilla</hi> as well as <hi>Aquila,</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Julia,</hi> and ſeveral others, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:100426:50"/>
               <p>This <hi>Old Diſciple of Chriſt,</hi> of whom I am now to ſpeak, had ſpent her years in the Fear and the Love of God, and full of Days; full of pleaſant quietneſs and hope ſhe is gone to Reſt: She calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sleeps till the Morning of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; when ſhe will have a Body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the marks of withering and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed Age; a Body full of Luſtre, full of Activity; and, <hi>Like to the glorious body of our Lord:</hi> Like the Angels that poſſeſs an eternal Youth, their Beams never dimly ſhine, their Light never weakly burns: After a long Circulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Hymns and Joys, their Praiſes are as cheerful, and their Voices as loud as ever.</p>
               <p>This aged Servant of our Lord, had made it her great buſineſs to truſt in him; and in the midſt of Revolutions, that were attended with threatning Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, ſhe remain'd unmoved: When others were frighted with Alarums, and the imagined approaches of Bloody Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſhe was undiſturb'd, ſaying, <hi>I have a good God, and I fear nothing;</hi> and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:100426:51"/>uſed to ſay, <hi>They are well kept that God keeps,</hi> for ſhe ſafely dwelt under the ſhadow of his Wings; and as one that knew, that the thoughts and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of worldly things, were very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable in a dying Hour, ſhe ſettled all her affairs before Death gave the laſt Summons, and ſo was prepared to dye.</p>
               <p>She poſſeſſed to almoſt an Hundred, a a very good Age, without pineing weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the ſorrows that cloud others, and ſend them early to the Grave: She was now and then afflicted, but ſhe was never overwhelmed.</p>
               <p>This good Woman ſpent her time in Prayer, and Reading of the <hi>Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> that beſt of Books, that great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyer of all Heavenly Light and Heat; Where are the gracious Souls, to whom this Revelation was not dear and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous? What ſort of People are thoſe, whoſe Ignorance and Rudeneſs forces them to Ridicule, what others lay their whole ſtreſs for another World upon? Dear to her, as well as to all other Holy Souls, was her <hi>Bible:</hi> there ſhe placed her truſt,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:100426:51"/>thence ſhe drew her Supports and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations. This was her <hi>Lanthorn</hi> in this World, during the darkneſs of her Pilgrimage; ſhe now needs it not, where there is everlaſting Day. Next to the Bleſſed Scripture, ſhe often read in Dr. <hi>Preſton,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sibbs,</hi> and in the Lives of <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> and ſome of their Works in <hi>Engliſh:</hi> On Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Reviving Names of Men, that were Stars of the firſt Magnitude, that ſhined in the Church! And when they were placed in ſuperiour Orbes, leſt their influence and heat behind; they ſtill edifie the Church by their Grave and Learned Writings, in which every thing is manly and ſubſtantial, and nothing ſlovingly or ridiculous, or trifling and unbecoming the Majeſty of Divinity, and the Character they bore: How much more happy were thoſe uſeful Men, in leaving ſuch ſolid Writings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them: then are ſome of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets of our days, who ſauce a great part of their Compoſures with Wit and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; or as I may ſay, with fooliſh Wit,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:100426:52"/>whilſt they content themſelves in dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up Vice with ſoft and eaſie Names; and accommodate every thing to the guſt and humour of a depraved Age; and do not ſo much Combat with Sin, as diſcover it; ſtudy more to pleaſe then to profit; their Books are Contagious, whilſt the Authors are alive; and when they dye, they do, like <hi>Nero,</hi> leave Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon behind them, and propagate infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for a long time together.</p>
               <p>Among all the reſt of the Old Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, ſhe had a particular reſpect to Dr. <hi>Preſton;</hi> which ſhewed, that ſhe had both a good Taſt and Judgment in Divine things. His ſolidity and wiſe management of truth, gave Light to her Underſtanding; and his ſerious and devout Applications warmed her Heart: And of all the Works of this <hi>Pious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> ſhe was moſt pleaſed and edified with his Diſcourſe about <hi>God's All-ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency;</hi> and ſo was another <hi>Old Diſciple,</hi> that I knew of <hi>above</hi> 90. that found al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways a peculiar refreſhment in that very Treatiſe. So wiſely did theſe Aged Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:100426:52"/>having ſorrowfully viewed the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of Life, and of all Creatures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themſelves to God alone, whoſe help they ſought, and whoſe help they found.</p>
               <p>As ſhe was careful to prepare her own Soul for another World, ſhe alſo thirſted for the welfare and happineſs of others; and often paſſed the moments that were moſt free from pain, in preſſing them to mind things of the greateſt and moſt laſting Conſequence, deſiring them to prepare to dye; and earneſtly moving them, in order to this, to live an Holy Life; fully thinking, with the great Apoſtle, that <hi>Without holineſs none can ſee the Lord.</hi> The ſight of the pure Majeſty of Heaven, would be amazing and aſtoniſhing to a Soul full of evil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations to objects terrene and ſenſual: Therefore this <hi>excellent Woman,</hi> did often deſire her Friends to <hi>take care leaſt they were in their way of living, like perſons walking in a Gallery, that went forwards and backwards without advancing any nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to their Journeys end;</hi> intimating,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:100426:53"/>that ſhe wiſht they might every day be nearer Heaven then they were before.</p>
               <p>With a mighty pleaſure, when I was once with her, ſhe diſcourſed of the forementioned famous Divines, and of the advantages ſhe had by the Preaching and Sermons of many worthy Men, ſuch as Mr. <hi>Burroughs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Lockyer,</hi> old Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> and ſeveral others, whom ſhe had long Survived. Her Lot indeed was caſt in happy times; and ſhe had the favour to live in the days of our Fore-fathers, when Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was more practiſed and eſteemed, then alas now it is. The <hi>Puritans</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputed leſs then we, and lived better: Oh that their <hi>Catholick Charity,</hi> their <hi>peaceable Spirit, and their innocent ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity</hi> might <hi>have a Reſurrection!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She lived to ſee moſt of her old Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance removed by Death, and ſo was, after having been ſatisfied with li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, very willing to depart, that ſhe and her Friends might meet again. She truſted God in her Health, and ſo ſhe died, when her Pain and Sickneſs came
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:100426:53"/>upon her. She often deſired one that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended her in her near approaches to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, to read <hi>the first words of the</hi> 40th <hi>Pſalm,</hi> as extremely ſuitable to her own Caſe and Temper. She was very humble and very patient in her illneſs; ſhe had no fretful diſordered Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ſhe bore her burden laid upon her by God; tho' her earneſt deſire to ſee him, made her now and then ſay, <hi>O why does he tarry?</hi> On her Sick Bed ſhe kept her Eye fixed above, and ſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her arrival at Heaven, her long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prayers thither; begging that her <hi>Iniquity might be blotted out,</hi> and <hi>wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be with Christ.</hi> And when her Daughter attending on her Miniſtred to her ſupport, with a language proper for one juſt in the cloſe of Life; and told her, God would receive her into the Arms of his Mercy; ſhe with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure of a Soul bordering upon Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, anſwered, <hi>She had laid her ſelf as the feet of Jeſus Chriſt, and had ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him, who was able to ſave to the uttermost;</hi> which words ſhe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:100426:54"/>often uttered in her former and latter Years. And a Night or two before ſhe was called away, ſhe repeated part of 39th <hi>Pſalm, Verſe</hi> 8, 9, 10. and ſuch was her Faith and Hope, that ſhe was able to apply to her ſelf, thoſe Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant words of that patient <hi>Job; I know that my Redeemer lives,</hi> and that ſhe ſhould <hi>ſee him for her ſelf,</hi> and this Redeemer ſhe is now gone to ſee: In his Arms we leave her, till he, and all that ſleep in him, ſhall come together at the laſt day.</p>
               <p>And now my Friends, from all that I have ſaid concerning this departed Saint, we may without any difficulty obſerve, that <hi>Meekneſs and Patience is the ready way to long Life:</hi> I do not believe this good Woman had lived ſo long, had ſhe not been of a calm and quiet Spirit. Thoſe that are furious and paſſionate, and ill-natured, corrode and vex them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and with haſt ſnap aſunder the Thread of Life. There are two things to be wondered at with reſpect to this Perſon: <hi>First,</hi> That ſhe ſhould live ſo
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:100426:54"/>long, as being one of the weaker and feebler Sex; and <hi>Secondly,</hi> That her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience ſhould not be tired during ſo long an abode in this World as 95 Years, but be continued to the laſt moment of her Life. How illuſtrious is that Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that kept ſo frail a Veſſel from being daſh't in pieces? How glorious is that Grace, that enabled her to perſevere in the Love of God?</p>
               <p>We may further conſider that Death is the Lot of all thoſe that are the moſt Aged, are not immortal; they moſt at length go to their Long Home, tho' many Thouſands go with quicker and more haſty ſteps then they. The Oak that is the oldeſt Father of the Foreſt, that has ſurvived many ſcorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Summers, and many cold blaſts of Winter, muſt at length feel the decays of Age; and periſh as ſurely, tho' not as ſoon as the little Trees: the longeſt day will have a concluding Night. Thoſe that are an <hi>hundred years old,</hi> and thoſe that are but <hi>Twenty,</hi> muſt both in a while lye down in a Bed of Duſt. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſalem</hi>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:100426:55"/>lived many long Years, but he did not live for ever. O let us, by the thought of this, be moved to lay hold on a Life that is Eternal; a Life that has no mixture of Corruption, and has no fears of decay, and ſuch a life the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed live in Heaven; there is no death.</p>
               <p>Again, Let none here fancy, becauſe they now and then hear of ſuch an one, that has attained to almoſt an Hundred, that therefore they ſhall live as long; and having ſuch a proſpect, may ſpend their preſent days in Jollities and Mirth, as believing they have an huge deal of time lying on their hands: For what a ſurprize will it be to ſtumble into the Grave in Youth, when they imagined they ſhould not come thither till they were Old. If you Examine the week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bills, you'll find few dye of Age comparatively, to what dye of other Diſeaſes; more dye before thirty, then live to Fourſcore. The youngeſt here have ſeen younger then themſelves ſnatcht away by Death; and many a Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is withered, when it juſt began to open.
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:100426:55"/>The Sun with many goes down at Noon: As well might every Diſciple of Chriſt expect to live as long as St. <hi>John,</hi> who was to tarry longer on Earth than moſt of the reſt, and Died at 93. <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> the Son of <hi>Cleophas,</hi> Brother of our Lord, lived an 120. Length of Life, is not of all other Bleſſings the moſt deſirable; and as one obſerves, it was not peculiar to Grace, or the Holy Line; for there are reckoned of the Fathers to the Flood Eleven Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but of the ſons of <hi>Adam</hi> by <hi>Cain,</hi> only Eight Generations ſo as the Poſterity of <hi>Cain may ſeem</hi> the longer lived. The good Men and good Women too, ſometime lived ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry long; as <hi>Abraham</hi> to One hundred ſeventy five, <hi>Iſaac</hi> to One hundred and Eighty, <hi>Jacob</hi> to One hundred forty ſeven: <hi>Sarah,</hi> whoſe years only among Women are Recorded, dyed in the One hundred twenty ſeventh year of her Age, an excellent Mother and a good Wife, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.36, 37. <hi>Anna</hi> is ſaid to be of a great Age, a very
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:100426:56"/>patient Perſon: For when ſhe was about Eighty four, ſhe departed not from the Temple.</p>
               <p>As to you that are the Relations of this good old Diſciple, do not wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Grave of your Friend with uſeleſs Tears: There is indeed great cauſe to Lament, when an uſeful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable Perſon is taken away by ſudden or untimely death; 'tis the falling of Fruit before Autumn come. But ſuch as have been a Bleſſing, and a long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Piety, to the very laſt ſtep of Humane Life, are not ſo to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, as having moſt regularly fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed their Courſe; and were not cut off in the middle of their Race. And yet, <hi>as one ſays,</hi> it is to be obſerved, that the Saints of God, tho' never ſo Old, and brought never ſo low through the Miſeries attending them, when they changed this Life for a better, were ſtill buried with great Lamentation. <hi>Abel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mizraim, Gen.</hi> 5. was a place never to be forgot, either by the <hi>Egyptians</hi> or the <hi>Canaanites;</hi> and not <hi>Jacob</hi> only, but
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:100426:56"/>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> were bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and great Publick Mournings made made.</p>
               <p>It would be very unreaſonable for you to Mourn, and needleſs for me to deſire you not to do it. She pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and longed to be with Chriſt, and would you mourn that God has heard her Prayers, and that <hi>ſhe now is where ſhe longed to be.</hi> It would be a moſt unjuſt thing to be ſorry that a Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer is gone to reſt, or to bewail the death of one that is Ninety Five; who was not gathered till the fulleſt time of Harveſt, and when ſhe was duely ripe for Glory. Oh be thankful that God has at length comforted this Handmaid of his, that waited for his Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Be thankful that you ſo long have had the benefit of her good advice, her ſhining example, and her holy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Let the remembrance of her Faith and Patience, and Hope, and her other excellent Qualifications kindle in you the like Graces. Conſider <hi>the end of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:100426:57"/>her Converſation,</hi> with what peace ſhe lived, and with what joy ſhe dyed. Do nothing unworthy of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of ſo good a Mother; tread in her ſteps, and follow her in the practiſe of all praiſe worthy things, that ſo ſhe and you may comfortably meet at the laſt day, and never never part again. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA's.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 5. <hi>line</hi> 5. <hi>after</hi> that <hi>Read</hi> it is. <hi>P.</hi> 13. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>for</hi> Eaden <hi>R.</hi> Endor. <hi>P.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>after</hi> it <hi>R.</hi> is <hi>P.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>R.</hi> Beaſts. <hi>P.</hi> 26. <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>R.</hi> Pillow. <hi>P.</hi> 36. <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>R.</hi> dwindling. <hi>P.</hi> 41. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>R.</hi> God's. <hi>P.</hi> 52. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>for</hi> thus <hi>R.</hi> this. <hi>P.</hi> 75. <hi>l.</hi> 21. <hi>R.</hi> Amiable. <hi>P.</hi> 88. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>after</hi> Land <hi>R.</hi> in Storms. <hi>P.</hi> 90. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>R.</hi> Amiableneſs.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>THE Changeableneſs of this World, with <hi>Reſpect to Nations,</hi> Families, and particular Perſons, with Practical Applications thereof to the various Conditions of this Mortal Life. <hi>By Timothy Rogers,</hi> M.A. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Salusbury</hi> at the <hi>Riſing Sun</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100426:57"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
